<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The unfortunate politique, first written in French by C.N. Englished by G.P.</title>
            <title>Cour sainte. Vol. 1, Book 4. English</title>
            <author>Caussin, Nicolas, 1583-1651.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1638</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 187 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 115 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18257</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4876</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107630</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843328</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843328</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8052</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18257)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8052)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1511:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The unfortunate politique, first written in French by C.N. Englished by G.P.</title>
                  <title>Cour sainte. Vol. 1, Book 4. English</title>
                  <author>Caussin, Nicolas, 1583-1651.</author>
                  <author>G. P., fl. 1638.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 192, 191-218, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by L. Lichfield for Ioseph Godwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>an. Dom. 1638.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>C.N. = Nicolas Caussin.</note>
                  <note>A translation of vol. 1, book 4 of: Cour sainte.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>A variant of the edition with imprint date 1639.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Herod --  I, --  King of Judea, 73-4 B.C. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8052:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> UNFORTUNATE POLITIQUE, Firſt written in French By C. N.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Engliſhed by</hi> G. P.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by L. LICHFIELD for IOSEPH GODWIN <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1638.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:8052:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8052:2"/>
            <head>TO THE COURTEOUS AND INGENIOUS <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou hast here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to thy accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, a briefe Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the moſt remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable Actions and Fortunes of this irreligious &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſperous Polititian: By Birth (as the moſt approved Authors con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend) an Idumean; a nation of moſt implacable malice and hostility, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God's choſen people; by uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation and borrowed title, a King of
<pb facs="tcp:8052:3"/> 
               <hi>Iudea;</hi> but in Fact and Goverment, a moſt bloody and barbarous tyrant: was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> affection to his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and alliance; (whereof <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his Treachery or Fury: without all civill or le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall regard of his people; and in one word, after the execution of thoſe Infant Martyrs, the fitteſt Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to haue involved the ſonne of God himſelfe (had that horrid at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of his been feaſable in one u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion maſſacre if innocent man kinde.</p>
            <p>The Almighty providence was pleaſed to exalt him to an higher ſtation, that like ſome malignant Contet or Prodigie of nature, hee might be more eminently diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and poſſeſse the remoteſt and dullest eyes, with admiration and horror. But a land: mark that ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a Rock, is as uſefull in navigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb facs="tcp:8052:3"/> as a compaſſe that guids directly, and examples inſtruct as well by avoidance as imitation: And if thoſe Ancients, that erected ſtatues and trophies by the way ſide, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the memory of their worthies did wiſely to place Gibbets there al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, to affright paſſengers with the memory of notorious malefactors; then certainly a moſt effectuall ſpur to Religion and Vertue may her drawn from the contemplation and horrour of this Monſters impleties and vices.</p>
            <p>The truth of the history being ſelected out of <hi>Ioſephus</hi> and other approved writers, may paſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further warrant: The collection and compoſition, which is as the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neaments and colours, (or indeed the ſpirit and motion of the picture) we owe to a forraine, but a judicious and fortunate Pencill, of one, whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:8052:4"/> name among the most diſcerning ſpirits, hath affectionately received the higheſt attributes, the judicious and eloquent <hi>Cauſinus;</hi> who collect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the materials and ſubstance from more ancient and authentick records, hath added ſhape and var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh according to the Idea of his own iudgement: And expoſing it to the world in a French attire; I preſume it will prove nothing the leſſe attra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> gracefull to an Engliſh eye. The habit it weares in Engliſh, it owes to a Tranſlatour, that needed not have ſuppreſſed his name, if his modeſty would permit him to accept that Testimony, which I think, hee hath iuſtly gained, to have retained in this laſt draught, (ſo neere as imitation can expreſse Copies, or a ſecond draught taken from a former Picture, can match that which was firſt taken from the face,) the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb facs="tcp:8052:4"/> and native beauty, and in this ſmall Peece to have had the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt hand.</p>
            <p>So that if either truth and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity of example, Art &amp; Elegancy of compoſition, Activeneſſe and life of expreſsion, Fidelity and Felicity of tranſlation may affect thee, I hope this ſhort Hiſtory, if it faile of thy applauſe and acclamation, ſhall aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly finde thy excuſe and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. To either of which, (as thy iudgement ſhall incline thee) I leaue it, and Thee (after an houre or two's vacancy to this recreation,) to thy more ſerious and uſefull employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:8052:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8052:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> VNFORTVNATE POLITIQUE, OR <hi>THE LIFE OF</hi> HEROD</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have caſt my eyes and thoughts on divers Hiſtories, but never could light on any that might better bring great ones really to apprehend how much they are deceived, who ſway a Court, or State by pure policie,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8052:6"/> and humane wiſdome, ſquaring religion to their own ends, and intereſts, then the life and death of this unfortunate King of <hi>Iury.</hi> Hee had a naturall judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a deep reach; an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that could pierce unto, and fathome the moſt wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and myſterious practices; &amp; a courage mounted to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degree and pitch that can bee expreſſed: A ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that had ſprung out of nothing, yet built his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes as high as a Throne, and eſtabliſhed it amidſt ſo various, ſo knotty, and intricate affaires, that he made himſelfe to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired even of the moſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding heads the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the world. But ſince he built on that impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous maxime, That hee ought to make Law and Religion his ſtal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:8052:6"/> for to ſerve his own purpoſes, hee led a life as full of villany, as diſquiet, which ended with the moſt wofull death that imagination can reach unto to conceive. What made me yet to reſolve upon this Hiſtory (which I have taken out of <hi>Ioſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus,</hi> and ſome other ſmaller fragments, and Commentaries, ſpinning it out according to the copiouſneſſe of my ſtyle, &amp; not ſtrictly tying my ſelfe to any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act tranſlation) was, that (beſide the <hi>Vnfortunate Politique</hi>) you read there Innocence perſecuted and wearied in the life of a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy that was the very mirrour of Patience; and whom I propoſe here in the firſt rank, as one of the greateſt Ornaments of our holy Court. It is not here with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8052:7"/> reaſon, that I would cull the faireſt Roſes amidſt the ſharpeſt Thornes; ſhew her ſerenity, and calmneſſe in the greateſt tempeſt of a troubleſome ſtate; and ſeek a hony Comb even in the jawes of a Lion: ſince from <hi>Herods</hi> Court I goe to fetch out a chaſt, and patient <hi>Mariamne,</hi> the very Tablet of Innocence moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpightfully entreated. The pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of this poore Queen de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to bee conſecrated with the pen of a Diamond to the Temple of Eternity; ſince it is able to ecclipſe the glory of the greateſt Heroes, to tranſcend the power of Rhetorick, and to ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh the ſpirits, even of thoſe that uſe not to admire ought that is obvious and vulgar. God who rayſes the glory of his choſen
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8052:7"/> on the foundation (as it were) of the greateſt miſeries, ſeeing the ſoule of this Princeſſe to be of a moſt hardy, and noble temper, thought fit to give her a ſpacious field for combat, that ſo ſhee might win the more glorious &amp; triumphant Palmes of patience: And to this end he gave her wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <hi>Herod</hi> to her husband, a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutor, a barbarous, and infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Executioner, but by ſo much the more ſutable to the patience of <hi>Mariamne,</hi> by how much the more like a Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and a Headſman then a huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and a head. To know the ſtrength, and roughneſſe of this anvill, we muſt know the ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer that beat upon it: The better to ſpeak the ſingular goodneſſe of this Queen, wee muſt oppoſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8052:8"/> unto it an anti-parallel, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of <hi>Herod;</hi> wee muſt obſerue how this diſloyall perſon, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his Life, Scepter, &amp; Crown from the houſe of <hi>Mariamne,</hi> in recompence thereof, took away from her both Scepter, Crown, and Life. After hee had ript out her bowels (as I may ſo ſpeak) putting to death her neereſt blood before her eyes, &amp; at laſt he flings her too, all weltring in her blood, upon the pile (where her kindred, and brethren were made a holocauſt) to bee the laſt ſacrifice to his helliſh furie; yet could he never ſhake her invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible patience, and conſtancy. Each one ſpeaks of <hi>Herod,</hi> as a man compoſed of clay tempered with blood, as of a Tyrant that would murther mercy it ſelfe:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8052:8"/> But every man knoweth not the art, and ſubtlety, which hee uſed to get into poſſeſſion of his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riamne,</hi> and <hi>Davids</hi> Scepter; op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing the one with all Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, and ſwaying the other with extream Tyranny.</p>
            <p>About fifty yeares before the Nativity of our Saviour, the kingdome of <hi>Iudah,</hi> that ſince <hi>David</hi> ſtood on its bottome neer a thouſand yeares (though in that period it oft had ſuffered ſtrange ecclipſes, &amp; changes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing often rent, and ſore ſhaken, &amp; by thoſe concuſſions often knit again, and took deeper root,) found its Tombe, and utter ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine in the fatall diſcord of two Brothers. <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> an honeſt man, but a bad King, did then beare rule: hee had neither
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8052:9"/> ſtrength, reſolution, nor courage; as coward like in his charge, as innocent in his manners, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. His over-facile de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour made him degenerate into a kinde of ſtupidity, and though unable to do any harm, yet did he ſuffer himſelfe to bee an inſtrument of all the inſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies that were committed, for that he was too ductile, &amp; capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the impreſſions of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Being apprehenſive of this his weakneſſe, hee caſts the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and burden of the Realme (with all willingneſſe) on the ſhoulder of his brother <hi>Aristo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulus,</hi> a man valiant, and hearty, but who had more imploiments then good ſucceſſe. During this declining and tottering ſtate of Royalty, <hi>Paleſtina</hi> was much ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:8052:9"/> and courted of her Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and aboue all, by <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pater</hi> (the father of this <hi>Herod</hi>) an <hi>Idumean</hi> by birth, in's man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners an <hi>Arabian,</hi> a factious ſpirit, well monied, and by his ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems able to overturne a great Empire; who had of a long time on foot a project upon the Realm of <hi>Iudea,</hi> he well foreſaw that it would be a hard taske for him to put in practiſe his wicked deſignes, as long as that bold Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> ſtood on the top, or pinacle; but if hee were once diſmounted, and <hi>Hircanus</hi> reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the throne, then all ſhould be at his arbitrement and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall. What doth the <hi>Arabian,</hi> but goe about ſowing the ſeeds of rebellion in the hearts of the people againſt their Leige Lord
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8052:10"/> 
               <hi>Aristobulus?</hi> Telling them, they were diſloyall cowards, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit their lawfull King <hi>Hircanus</hi> to be dethroned (in whoſe hand nature had put the Scepter,) and the Kingdome to be transferred on a mutinous, and a turbulent ſpirit, who ere long would make them the wracks &amp; deſolation of all <hi>Paleſtine;</hi> that they had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned a King, whom they could not tax with ought, but exceſſe of goodneſſe, to admit of one, who having entred at the gate of treachery, could not reigne over them without the trouble, and combuſtion of his country, when good <hi>Hircanus</hi> would deveſt himſelfe of his right, they were to blame to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcend to his modeſty, who was by ſo much the worthier to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8052:10"/> rule, by how much he deem'd himſelfe the more unworthy: The glory which hee did fly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in undervaluing his own perſon, ſhould have purſued him to his grave. If they did object againſt him too much gentleneſſe, it was the more agreeable to the piety, and ſweet behaviour of the <hi>Iews.</hi> If the <hi>Doues</hi> were to chuſe them a King, they would ever make a choiſe of a Stalue, before a Sparrow-hawk. This ſubtile head, by ſuch like remonſtrances found many that gave eare unto him, partly amongſt thoſe that loved innovation, &amp; partly too, among thoſe that were carried away with the pretended juſtice of the cauſe, &amp; none would yet eſpie his drift, which under the colour of publique good, went
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8052:11"/> about to erect a Monarchy for himſelfe, or his heires. Having now thruſt the iron ſo farre into the fire, hee ſtudied how to win the heart of <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> with all manner of obſequiouſneſſe, and teſtimonies of friendſhip, which was not difficult to purchaſe; this Prince permitting himſelfe to be overruled by thoſe that would make any ſemblance of good will towards him.</p>
            <p>Behold him now (become as it were) Lord Protector, or Guardian of this flexible ſpirit, when under pretence of love he poſſeſſes in that manner, that all the actions of <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> paſt cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant no longer by any other au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, then the directions and counſells of <hi>Antipater.</hi> Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe when he began to egge
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8052:11"/> him forward for to make warre on his brother for the recovery of the royall Throne, hee found his heart ſo far benumbd that he had much adoe to warm it, and ſtrike a ſpark of courage into his ſoule, for the exceſſive coldneſſe and the unmanlineſſe of his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. But at length hee preacht one day effectually, and did edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie much, telling him, that this quitting of his kingdome, which he had tranſlated to his brother, was a thing that could not ſtand with his Honour, and ſafety of Life. What eye would not diſtill teares to ſee him in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, &amp; miſery, while his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lived in riot, and pomp: This was to confound the Laws of nature; this was to authorize tyranny. Petty theeves are caſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:8052:12"/> into a Dungeon, or Stocks, and <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> that had uſurpt a kingdome, rufled in ſilk, &amp; ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kled with Diamonds.</p>
            <p>A Kingdome was a ſhirt which a man ſhould not ſhift off, but with his life: they were the tales and dreames of idle talking Philoſophy, that Crowns were lin'd with thorns, whereas they are Rubies &amp; Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, that never yet moleſted any mans head. The life which then <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> lead, would bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter become an <hi>Eſsean Monk,</hi> or a <hi>Capuchin,</hi> then a King: And to conclude, that all the people de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired with paſſion to ſee him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſtated in his fathers Throne. Hee poſſeſt his eares with ſo powerfull Rhetorique, that hee began now to gaine upon him
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8052:12"/> But there were many reaſons, which held him in ſuſpenſe. The one was his oath, by which hee had renounced his Royalty; the other want of ſufficient ſtrength for the enterpriſe. For the oath, <hi>Antipater</hi> ſoon reſolved him of that, telling him, he ſwore a hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous crime, and there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could obliege him to the performance; and for ſtrength, he acquainted him with the aux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iliary forces of luſty <hi>Arabians,</hi> which he could levy at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. While hee yet ſtaggerd at this unſteedy footing, he went on to breath into his heart black miſtruſts, and jealouſies touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his brother, as though (after he had preyed upon his eſtate) he had an enterprize upon his life; ſurmiſing conſpiracies to be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8052:13"/> plotted againſt him: and this hee did with ſuch art, &amp; ſleight, that <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> yeelded to him, and gave him full commiſſion of war, or peace, to doe according as it liked him beſt. This conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the Apple of diſcord was flung into the midſt: <hi>Antipater</hi> fail'd not to implore the ayd of <hi>Aretas</hi> King of the <hi>Arabs,</hi> who comes up with a mighty army, which like an inundation over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runs all <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> committing over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runs all <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> committing all outrage, and hoſtility, ſacking &amp; depopulating (without mercy) all the way he went, inſomuch, that hee drove <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> to a very narrow ſtrait, beſeiging him within <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolis, and Royall City.</p>
            <p>But as the greater Serpent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours the leſſer; ſo hapneth it
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8052:13"/> hereupon, that the <hi>Romans</hi> under the conduct of <hi>Pompey</hi> the Great, now diſplaying their dreadfull Eagles on the plaines of <hi>Syria,</hi> lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding an army of fire, before which all other Roytlets or minor Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were but as chaffe, make this <hi>Arabian</hi> glad to retire within his own territories, they march on vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoriouſly without controle, and interpoſe themſelves to preſcribe laws, to pronounce peace, or war, how, and to whom ſoever they pleaſed. The two brothers made all Courtſhip to the <hi>Roman,</hi> to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe his favour, and amity; each one ſtriving eagerly to win him of his ſide, well perceiving that the obtaining of this would ſpeedily put a period to the controverſie. <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> (as the more generous hold, and King-like) at the firſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſefound the more favour, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8052:14"/> that among other largeſſes, he preſented him with a vine al of maſſie gold, one of the rareſt, and moſt exact workmanſhip in the world, which afterward, for a long time ſerved for an ornament in the Capitoll. At length behold both brothers proſtrate at <hi>Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pey's</hi> feet, conteſting both, &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding not for a Hamlet, or Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, but a Kingdome; nothing ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting that while they ſtaked their fortunes in the hands of a ſtranger, (who knew no other law but his ambition) inſteed of Um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire he would play the Vulture, &amp; claſp them in his tallons. <hi>Antipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> ſeeing at firſt the ballance to perpend to <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> his ſide, as one that the <hi>Romans</hi> had reaſon to hope would be more ſerviceable, &amp; advantagious to their deſignes, never ceaſed to decry him, to caſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8052:14"/> black aſpertions on his reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to work the <hi>Romans</hi> to a miſtruſt of his inclination towards them, ſtill fawning, and couching like a Spaniell before <hi>Pompey:</hi> inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that <hi>Aristobulus</hi> foreſeeing that this pernicious ſpirit, abuſing the name, &amp; weakneſſe of his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, would ſel both to the <hi>Roman,</hi> ſets himſelfe on his gard; where he had but too much reſolution, and too little ſtrength to cope with the Army of ſo potent an Empire. This poore Prince being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matched, and ſinking under the weight of ſuch an encounter, was taken captive, bound in chaines with his two ſoones and ſo many daughters, and led away to <hi>Rome</hi> to furniſh a triumph for <hi>Pompey: Ieruſalem</hi> is made tributary, the Pontificate confer'd upon <hi>Hyrca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> but all the authority commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:8052:15"/> to the hands of <hi>Antipater.</hi> This was a ſpectacle that drew teares eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from thoſe, who before times could not affect <hi>Aristobulus,</hi> to ſee this unfortunate King in bolts, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with iron, together with his Princely ſonnes, and the poor La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies his daughters, all the heires of their fathers misfortunes who were, leaving their native country, where they reigned in ſuch Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, for to ſeek through ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couth and tedious voyages by ſea &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and, their thraldome or death, which is the more ordinary wiſh of unhappy wights.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antipater</hi> reapes the bayes of this victory, and begins (though as yet ſtaind with blood) to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh his litle Monarchy which he had been ſo long a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>triving. <hi>Hyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus</hi> ſeem'd like an old ſepulcher which retain'd nothing but the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8052:15"/> name, or inſcription. All things were effected by him in appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, though not any thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed: The other entertain'd the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> out of his Exchequer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed preſents, ſent, and received Embaſſadours, practiſed confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racies, corrupted the forces of his adverſaries and rid his way of all the rubs, and impediments that might oppoſe his advancement, &amp; greatneſſe; and made it beleeved that this mild Pontiffie was prime mover and author of all. Then ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe each day to grow ſtronger in repute and authority, the better to aſſure the Realme for his ſonnes after his deceaſe, hee made the elder (namely <hi>Phaſelus</hi>) governour of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and on <hi>Herod</hi> his younger ſon he confer'd the Prefectureſhip of <hi>Galile.</hi> In ſhort time after, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had ſuckt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8052:16"/> up all the winde with his flatulent ambition had engendred, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now at his <hi>non ultra,</hi> not knowing which way to bend his machinations, he ſuckt up a glaſſe of poyſon that was miniſted unto him at a feaſt by the device of <hi>Malicus</hi> his enemie. Behold here the iſſue of humane practices! Thoſe who are drunk with ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and are mad for Honours which they ſeeke to arrive at by miſchievous plots, and all the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell of body and minde, are like thoſe litle bubbles which ariſe on the ſurface of the water in a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt, they ſwell, and burſt in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Antipater</hi> being dead, his two ſonnes, <hi>Phaſelus</hi> and <hi>Herod</hi> ſhare equally in the ſucceſſion, each of them maintaines his own ſtation firmly, &amp; ſtudies to temper the matter ſo as to get <hi>Hyrcanus</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:8052:16"/> ſtill to act the ſame part to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent a King. <hi>Herod</hi> was no ſooner entred upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his charge, even while his father was yet living (being not full fifteen yeares of age) ſhewed early what in time hee would prove by ſome excurſions of his inbred diſpoſition, which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times hee made to ſallie out, like thoſe litle ſtreaks, and ſparks of heat in the ayre, that burſt out of a cloud, and then after flaſh in lightning. He was of a fraudulent, and malignant ſpirit, ambitious e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to a degree of madnes, whoſe fingers did alwaies itch to bee im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brued in blood, and ſlaughter; and indeed he ſtained his tender years and the prologue of his reigne with effuſion of humane blood, putting to the ſword <hi>Ezekias,</hi> who indeed lived in the eſteem of a Rover &amp; common robber, but
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:8052:17"/> he cut in peeces many other <hi>Iews</hi> with him without diſcerning the guiltleſſe, fed the guilty, which cauſed that many innocent ſoules were involv'd in this common ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine. The mothers of theſe people who were maſſacred by <hi>Herod,</hi> ſtirr'd not out of the Temple, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting, and with their heire di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheveld, demanding juſtice from <hi>Hyrcanus,</hi> who was but an Idoll, or Statue of Majeſtie. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding being importun'd with the cryes of theſe diſtreſſed wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, &amp; ſet on by ſome of his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, he cauſed <hi>Herod</hi> to be ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond for to appeare in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. In this action it was well that this young Prince ſhewed ſome reſolution, and gave ſome aſſurance of courage. Others that were accuſed came to this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Iudea,</hi> all ſad &amp; dejected,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8052:17"/> but he arrived thither as to a feaſt or Theatre, attended with a flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing convoy clad in Skarlet, all perfum'd and his haire frizel'd, &amp; moreover with Letters of recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation from the <hi>Romans,</hi> which were writ in the ſtile of au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and military language, commanding the Iudges to acquit him without any further proceſſe. Hee was ſcarce fifteen yeares of age, and yet with his very preſence daſht the Iudges, and Advocates ſo out of countenance that of all thoſe that had provided long ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranges againſt him, there was not one that durſt open his mouth while he was there. One of the Iudges whoſe name was <hi>Sameas,</hi> a right honeſt man, and of more courage then all the reſt, ſpake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud to King <hi>Hyrcanns,</hi> who was there preſent: Idoe not wonder
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8052:18"/> that this young Lord appeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this Tribunal in ſuch equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page every man would ſecure him ſelfe as well as he may; but I doe wonder Sir, that you and your Counſell ſhould omit this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanour, as if he came hither not to be judg'd, but to cut the Iudges throats. You will now pardon him in favour, but he will one day aſſacinate you in juſtice. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed of this whole Senate there ſcap'd not one that <hi>Herod</hi> did not put to death, when he had got the full power of the kingdome, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept him onely that had delivered his opinion of him with this bold ſimplicity. It is recorded of this <hi>Sameas,</hi> how that ſome yeares af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a queſtion being made of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving <hi>Herod</hi> to bee their King; when others did ſtiffely oppoſe it, he ſpake freely that hee gave his
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8052:18"/> ſuffrage to <hi>Herod,</hi> &amp; as they were wondring at the ſpeech, marvell not at the matter (quoth he) God would give you a King in his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and hee could not finde one naughtier then <hi>Herod:</hi> He is the ſcourge which you doe want to chaſtiſe your infidelity. <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> then ſeeing the Iudges ſomewhat animated by the ſpeech of <hi>Sameas</hi> and to be more inclined to the ſide of luſtice then Mercy, made him ſecretly to ſlink away, for hee lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him intirely, and ſo hatcht the egge of a Cockatrice within his own boſome. <hi>Herod</hi> who came not any way behind his Father in pollicie, following his examples and practices adhered firmly unto the <hi>Romans,</hi> winning them by all manner of obſervances, and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> with all plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance, and flattery. The kingdome
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8052:19"/> of <hi>Iudea</hi> ſeemd as yet to bee farre enough from his reach, <hi>Phaſelus</hi> as the elder held the better part of it: <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> whom you have ſeen led away in chaines to <hi>Rome,</hi> had yet two ſonnes, whereof the elder call'd <hi>Alexander</hi> was father to chaſt <hi>Mariamne,</hi> whoſe pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence we doe here blazon; the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was <hi>Antigonus,</hi> who ſpunne <hi>Herod</hi> a ſpindle full of matter to untwiſt. But hee was ſoone rid of both; for unfortunate <hi>Alexander</hi> ſucceſſour of his father <hi>Aristobu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> his diſaſters, being come to the field with certaine forces, which he had pickt up as well as his weak fortunes enabled him, was oppreſt by the <hi>Romans,</hi> who came to the aſſiſtance of <hi>Herod. Antigonus</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing got looſe from captivity, wherein he was detained at <hi>Rome,</hi> together with his father <hi>Ariſtobu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:8052:19"/> cut out much employment too for <hi>Herod.</hi> For caſting himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the armes of the <hi>Parthians,</hi> hee made them ſo many promiſes, and ſwel'd them with ſuch hopes that they undertook to inveſt him with the kingdome: and forthwith they made preparations by Sea &amp; Land, and prevailed ſo far both by force, and cunning, that they chaſed out <hi>Hyrcanus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Phaſelus: Herod</hi> very narrowly eſcapt his life, and though he had a courage of ſteele, yet was hee ſo amaz'd with this ſurpriſe, that hee went very neer to make himſelf away. <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> was very courſly hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the command of his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew <hi>Antigonus,</hi> he had his eares cropt off, and ſo was made fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver uncapable of the Pontificate. <hi>Phaſelus, Herods</hi> brother, being ſo enraged with this unexpected
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:8052:20"/> chance of fortune, daſht his brains againſt a ſtone.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod,</hi> who had alwaies ſtuck as cloſe to the <hi>Romans,</hi> as the lvy to the wall, ſeeing his affaires in ſuch a plunge &amp; extream hazard, implores their aid, and complains in moſt pathetick expreſſions of the violence of <hi>Antigonus,</hi> the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſions, and hoſtility of the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> puts them in minde of the good ſervices of his father <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pater,</hi> and promiſes on his part the Ocean, and all the ſcaly Legions. Which letters found ſo good ſucceſſe, that he (beyond all hopes and expectation) was proclaimed King of <hi>Iudea,</hi> and <hi>Antigonus</hi> an enemy to the <hi>Roman</hi> eſtate becauſe a fugitive, and allyed to the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians. Herod</hi> purſues him with hue &amp; cry, being aſſiſted with the forces of the <hi>Roman Empire. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigonus</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:8052:20"/> ſtill unfortunate in all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventures, after a fierce encounter, and long reſiſtance was taken pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, and was the firſt of any king that by the command of <hi>M. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony</hi> was executed in a manner ſo unbefitting his quality, and to the <hi>Romans</hi> unuſuall, leaving his head upon a ſcaffold in the City of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch,</hi> for no other reaſon then ſeeking to recover his fathers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance: But <hi>Strabo</hi> ſaith that <hi>M. Anthony</hi> knew no other way to make <hi>Herod</hi> to bee agniz'd for King; both for that there were yet living ſome of the blood Royall, that were capable of the Scepter; and for that the people loved their naturall King, but hated the ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
            <p>This Tragoedy ended, <hi>Herod</hi> mounted on the top of fortunes wheele. Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all the thornes in his
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:8052:21"/> way (as he thinks) now grub'd up. There now remained of the Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious race of the <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſmoneans,</hi> but an aged &amp; weather-beaten Prince, one infant Boy, and two Girles to bee defeated. <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> was that aged Prince, who intruth drew an unwilling breath, whoſe head many turmoiles, and viciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of fortune haſtned his hoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry haire, he was then held captive in the <hi>Parthians</hi> hands; but the King, though a <hi>Barbarian,</hi> had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion on a milde, debonaire na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in ſo deplor'd a caſe, ſo that hee permitted him to live within the walls of <hi>Babylon,</hi> with all the liberty as might be deſired. This poor Prince who lived all his life time without any ambition did beare this change of fortune with an equall temper, and tenor of minde. The <hi>Iews</hi> who lived in that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8052:21"/> Kings dominions ſeeing him ſo maim'd, and in a manner excoria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with ſtripes, poore &amp; forlorn, yet gave him the reſpect of a King and expreſſed ſuch honour, and reverence towards him, that hee found a kingdome (in a manner even in his captivity.) <hi>Herod</hi> who ſaw that this man might ſtand him yet in ſome ſteed againſt thoſe that could diſquiet and annoy his anxious and unſetled eſtate diſpat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth an Embaſſadour ſtrait to the King of the <hi>Parthians,</hi> with many faire preſents, and Letters fraught with ſugred words, and ſoothing complements; wherein hee doth beſeech him not to bereave him of that onely and beſt contentment that he had in the world but to ad this curteſie unto his former fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours wherewith hee had obliged him: <hi>Hyrcanus,</hi> ſaith hee, was his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:8052:22"/> good Benefactor, his Protector, &amp; Father, and ſince God had now given ſome repoſe unto his affairs, it would be a ſingular comfort un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him to communicate the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the cares and pleaſures of a King with one ſo truſty &amp; ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be beloved. The <hi>Parthian</hi> King willing to gratifie <hi>Herod</hi> whom he ſaw to be ſupported by the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire (which he did more feare for its puiſſance, then honour for its valour) granted full leave to <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> to goe whither he would. He (good man) conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the principall men of his nation, who did altogether diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him from it, but the eaſines of his good nature (which did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſwallow the bait without heeding the hooke) yeelded to thoſe ſuppoſed curteſies of <hi>Herod,</hi> and ſo returned ſtraight to <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:8052:22"/> where hee was received with all demonſtrations of joy, &amp; ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Behold no wall the Royall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily in the hands of this barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous uſurper. <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> had but one daughter, who took not after her father kinde, for ſhee was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream haughty, and in this ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude did fret, and champ upon the bit, with much diſcontent, ſhe was the mother of two children, a Boy and a Girle, his name was <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulus,</hi> and hers <hi>Mariamne,</hi> who was after married to <hi>Herod. Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amne</hi> was eſteemed the moſt beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Princeſſe in the world. For <hi>Gellius</hi> who went about to ſurvey the rareſt features in the world, for to return a Liſt of them to <hi>M. Anthony,</hi> having well ſcan'd the moſt excellent pieces of Nature, when he ſaw <hi>Mariamne,</hi> he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted that all other beauties were
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:8052:23"/> courſe, &amp; caſt in a mould of earth, in compariſon of this which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to him to have dropt from the ſpheres, &amp; to have been drawn by ſome divine, and immortall Limmer. This man ſaw but the bark, and casket, and yet was ravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with admiration; but her comelineſſe of body was nothing in compariſon of the noble quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of her ſoule. This was a tender Imp of the ſtock of the famous <hi>Machabees,</hi> well verſt in Gods laws, diſcreet, modeſt, &amp; reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, that as <hi>Suſanna,</hi> but aboue all couragious and patient; living in the Court of <hi>Herad</hi> as <hi>Iob</hi> upon the dunghill. Never was beauty, &amp; goodneſſe ſo diſcountenanc'd, &amp; unhappy in the fortunes of one perſon. This creature that might have been courted by ſo many Princes, that might have had ſuch
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:8052:23"/> attendance ever ready at her feet, had now <hi>Herod</hi> for her Lord, who had nothing of a man but skin, &amp; ſhape; and it was even all one to couple the Lamb with the Lion, the Dove with the Hawk, and tye the living to the dead, joyning the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mouth to mouth, as to wed ſuch a Lady to ſuch a Monſter. But hee that had now the power in his own hand, ſues for her very paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionatly, both for her unparallel'd beauty, and moreover the better to ſtrengthen his eſtate, conſidering that the alliance of this young La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, who deſcended from ſo great kindred, would adde honour to him, and his houſe, who was but lately ſprung up, and might make him to place more confidence in the <hi>lews,</hi> and make them more lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and loyall to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> the Grandfather of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:8052:24"/> 
               <hi>Mariamne,</hi> and <hi>Alexandra</hi> her mother, ſeeing that <hi>Herod</hi> had now got his head aboue the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and was become maſter of his affaires, having now got the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into his own hands, although by tyranny, and intruſion; yet they meaſuring all by his place, &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, not by his perſon and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, judg'd that this marriage might be yet for their advantage, and that his wife might ſupple his harſh nature, and make him more favourable to the Royall houſe. This noble maid fore-ſaw well that to put her into the hands of <hi>Herod,</hi> was to caſt her into the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons jawes: But not to contradict thoſe to whom ſhee owed her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and to obey the lawes of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, ſhee ſubmitted her neck to the yoke, fortifying her royall heart againſt all the ſtormes that
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:8052:24"/> ſeemed to threaten &amp; come thron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging upon her. Behold her now married! <hi>Herod</hi> loues her, as the Huntſman doth his Veniſon for his own ends, and benefit: not loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing by love one graine of his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ambition, or cruelty. This perverſe thing held a kingdome like a woolfe by the eares, ſtill fic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle, and ſhaking, and when his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires ſeemed to be well ſetled, hee ſtudied nothing but how to rid himſelfe of thoſe, whom hee had ſtript naked of their fortunes, and ſtrength. His Queen could finde no reſpect, nor could ſhe any whit mollifie, and reclaim his ſavage conditions; hee ſhewed how litle affection he bare to her ſoly, when he wrought for his own pretended intereſts, at that time when it was debated whom to Surrogate to be grand Pontifie in liew of <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:8052:25"/> who (by his late deformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) being irregular in the law, was excluded from the Altar. <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> ſaw every day before his eyes in his own Court young <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulus,</hi> the only brother of his wife a Prince every way accompliſht, and generally deſigned for the <hi>Tiare,</hi> yet he caſts his eyes abroad and goes to ſeek beyond <hi>Euphra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> in the City of <hi>Babylon</hi> a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne <hi>Iew</hi> named <hi>Ananell,</hi> &amp; cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated him chiefe Prieſt. This was a pill which <hi>Alexandra</hi> the mother of <hi>Ariſtobulus,</hi> and <hi>Mariamne</hi> could not eaſily ſwallow. It was in vain to candy o're the buſineſſe: Shee ſaw manifeſtly the rejection of her houſe, in that her ſon (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſo many obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) was in a manner diſpoſſeſt of an honour, which blood &amp; nature, and the generall vote of the world
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:8052:25"/> did call him unto, and to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on a man of no worth, no repute. Shee could not well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe her anger from breaking out, and that in a higher ſtraine then the miſeries of the times, and malice of <hi>Herod</hi> would ſuffer un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtioned. <hi>Mariamne</hi> all this while injoying the tranquility of her noble minde, goes upon a day unto the King, and with her natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall gracefulneſſe, and ſweet carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age tells him, that the prop, &amp; ſtay of her houſe was ſore fhaken, and greatly weakned, &amp; at the preſent in ſuch a plight that ſhe had no joy to hold a Scepter any longer: She deſired only ſhee might quit the world with honour: Had he then beſtowed the Miter on her bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he had advanced a creature, whom he could not ſtand in feare of, his Scepter being thereby the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:8052:26"/> more ſecured, and of whom hee could not (in all reaſon) but hope the beſt, who was but young, and tender as wax (being in his own hand) ſhe could temper, and ſtamp what impreſſions he pleaſed. This act would haue made him reigne in hearts as well as Provinces, when men ſhould ſee him the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and protectour of the young ſon of <hi>Hyrcanus,</hi> whoſe vertues he had alwaies hououred. Laſtly, that the honor which did redound to her by his alliance could not ſeem to her conſummate, ſo long as ſhe ſaw her own blood debar'd from thoſe honours, and promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which he could place them in, without any prejudice to his own eſtate.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> ſuffred himſelfe to bee wonne for that time by the char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming language of <hi>Marinmne,</hi> and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:8052:26"/> when he had well pondred the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, after mature deliberation, he reſolved to confer the Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate on young <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in law, which was performed with great ſolemnity. He aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles his friends in the Pallace hall; then calling for <hi>Alexandra,</hi> hee made a ſet ſpeech againſt her in the preſence of them all, much co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of her behaviour, and tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them that ſhe ſtudied nothing but how to thwart, and diſquiet his affaires, and to take from him a Scepter which Heaven made him to purchaſe with much travell, &amp; ſweat, for to put it into the hands of an Infant to the prejudice of the Queen her daughter: neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he could forget injuries, but could not forget his nature, which was to doe well to thoſe that ſought to doe him harme. Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:8052:27"/> and confirmation hereof, hee conferres the Pontificate on her ſon, his purpoſe being never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other, and the Surrogation of <hi>Ananel</hi> made with no other inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then to continue for a time, while hee did expect the child ſhould grow to riper yeares. This poore mother ambitious accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to and beyond the nature of her ſex (upon this tender of the Pontificate) was ſo tranſported with joy, that her heart melted at her eyes, and thereupon avowed freely to <hi>Herod,</hi> that ſhe attempted all the means poſſible to retain the <hi>Tiare</hi> in the royall houſe, judging it a matter very unbefitting to transfer it another way: but as for the Kingdome that ſhe never pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended any right to it, &amp; that ſuch deſignes were farre from her thoughts: when it would pleaſe
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:8052:27"/> God to ſequeſter her from the world ſhe would dye with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented heart, leaving her ſon great Pontifie, and her daughter Queen. Moreover if ſhe had laſht it out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the bounds of duty and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency in uncivill ſpeeches, that ſhe was excuſable, as being a mother very tenderly affected towards a ſon that deſerv'd to bee belov'd, the mother in law of a King to whom ſuch a neer affinity would permit ſome more liberty of ſpeech, and the daughter of a King to whom ſervitude was ſuch a tough morſell, that her ſtomacke could not well digeſt: and ſince he did deal fo friendly with her, that he ſhould have no occaſion hence forth to complain of her contu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy, and diſobedience. Hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they joyne hands, and behold them now very good friends. But
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:8052:28"/> alas how like are the friendſhips of this world to the felicity of it: Worldly friendſhip is fickle &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull, &amp; worldly felicity hangs on a rotten Cable, and hath its foundation on the Quick-fands. This poore mother rejoyced for a little tickling of her ambition, but could not perceive that her ſonne was not a Prieſt indeed, but a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to the cruelty of <hi>Herod.</hi> Wiſe <hi>Mariamne,</hi> who by long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience had learn't to hold pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity ſtil in ſuſpicion, would not permit her heart to be ſo dilated, nor give the reynes to her joyes, but that ſhee arm'd her ſelfe each day againſt the revolt of fottune. The feaſt of Tabernacles which is ſo ſolemnly celebrated among the <hi>Iews,</hi> being come, <hi>Ananel</hi> after he had ſerved a while for a Cipher is ſhamefully diſcarded. <hi>Ariſtobu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:8052:28"/> begins to exerciſe his function: He was then but ſeventeen yeares of age, but of a very tall ſtature, well proportion'd, and ſtreight as a Palm-tree, glorious as a Star, and very much reſembling his father: When the people ſaw him accou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in his Pontificalibus, which were full of Majeſty, marching up to the Altar, and performing his office with ſuch gravity and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, hee ſeem'd to them like a new Sunne that iſſued out of the Clouds, and came to guild the world, which was before enwrapt in gloomy darkneſſe. The hearts of al the <hi>Hebrews</hi> which had groa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned under the preſſures of civill warres, did now ſpread like Roſes by the favourable aſpect of this young Pontifie. His naturall comelineſſe enchafed (as it were) within his Majeſtich Robes did
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:8052:29"/> caſt an incredible luſter, and ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, which did dazle the eyes of the ſpectators. Some beheld him with a wiſt, and earneſt look, remaining like ſtatues, but yet their teares prov'd that their eyes were not of marble. Others did betray their affections by many dumb emblems, and inarticulate expreſſions. Others gave vent to their joyes, and their mouthes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered what their hearts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd; not being able to forbeare acclamations, though ſomewhat too free in reſpect of the times; yet pardonable in their ſimple af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. They call'd to minde the proweſſe of thoſe ancient <hi>Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabees,</hi> who had redeem'd them from Idolatry; they knew how that poore <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> was but a Ghoſt, or ſhadow ſurviving his own funerall. They had freſh in
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:8052:29"/> memory the Grandfather of this young Pontifie, the great <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulus,</hi> who was led away mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cled, and faſt bound in cords like a Gallie-ſlave to <hi>Rome.</hi> They were not ignorant how that <hi>Alexander</hi> his father, and his uncle <hi>Antigonus</hi> had loſt their lives in oppoſing the uſurpation of a ſtranger. This young Prince alone remain'd, that had eſcapt ſo many wracks, and they ſaw that in his youth did live and ſpring forth the hopes of their country, and (as it is eaſie to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what we love) they perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded themſelves, that <hi>Herod</hi> who at the beginning demanded the Realme in the name of this young Prince <hi>Ariſtobulus,</hi> was now to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſh the booty, yeelding to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and right. And for this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, they did expreſſe their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe with the more freedome.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:8052:30"/> But the ignorant multitude were far out in their accompts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> having well obſerv'd the poſture of this peoples counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, ſaw that to talke out-right according to maxims of ſtate, or to make a grave morall ſpeech, would have ſavoured ſomewhat of a Clark, (and this was not his method or ordinary ſtile) but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters into a furious jealouſie, &amp; cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Pontifie, and his mother, and his own wife to be ſo narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly watcht, and their actions pried into, that they could not wag a fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger but he was advertis'd thereof. The prudent <hi>Mariamne,</hi> among theſe ſuſpicions, ſtill living in good reſpect, appeaſing diſcontents on either party, as much as her em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments would permit her: But her mother <hi>Alexandra</hi> being prickt to the heart to ſee her ſelfe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:8052:30"/> among ſo many ſpies, and eves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>droppers, who ever uſed, and ſtill would faine converſe with Royall freedome, reſolv'd to play ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, either to quit loſſes, or to double them, and to break the bonds of her ſpecious ſervitude, or to offer her neck to <hi>Herods</hi> fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chion. So high a point did her mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries carry her to! In this extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, what doth ſhee? <hi>Cleopatra</hi> that Queene, whoſe name had tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel'd the world over, and fill'd it with the noiſe, was at that time in <hi>Aegypt;</hi> and ſhe hated <hi>Herod</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally, both for his barbarous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and for ſome reſpects of her own: for ſhee underſtood by good intelligence that he had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termedled in her affaires, and had counſell'd <hi>M. Anthony</hi> to forſake her, yea, and to take away her life too. This Tyrant was ſo accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom'd
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:8052:31"/> to the word Kill, that hee preſcribes eaſily to others thoſe remedies which himſelfe us'd for his own maladies. 'Tis a ſtrange memorable thing that <hi>Cleopatra</hi> being to paſſe one day through <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea,</hi> he took a reſolution to ſend her to another world, thinking to gratifie <hi>Mark. Anthony</hi> by this meanes: but his friends diſſwaded him from it, telling him it was an enterpriſe too raſh, and difficult, &amp; able to ruine his fortunes eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. But yet the project was never diſcovered. <hi>Cleopatra</hi> had but too much reaſon to hate <hi>Herod:</hi> which did embolden diſtreſſed <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra</hi> to write unto her in theſe tearmes.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="letter">
               <body>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:8052:31"/>
                  <head>ALEXANDRA to Queen CLEOPATRA <hi>Sends Greeting.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>MADAM</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>SInce God hath made you to be borne with that advantage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all other Queenes for emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent qualities, it ſtands with good reaſon, that your greatneſſe ſhould ſerve as a refuge, and Sanctuary to the innocent, and an Altar to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable perſons. Poore <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra</hi> that hath much innocence without ſupport, and too much miſery without all ſuccour, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, caſts her ſelfe into the armes of your Majeſtie, &amp; is now become your ſuppliant not for the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:8052:32"/> recovery of a Scepter, but for the ſecurity of her life, and the life of her ſon, which is the moſt preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous gage, and pledge of heavens bounty, that was now left her. Your Majeſtie is not ignorant how that fortune made mee the daughter and mother of a King, but <hi>Herod</hi> hath reduc'd me to the ranke, and condition of Maid-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. I am not ambitious of my ſuffering which I had rather diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble, then with oſtentation re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat, but all that a ſlave can endure in a Galley, doe I undergoe in a Kingdome, by the in humanity of a ſon in law, who having ſnatcht the Diadem into his hands, would faine deprive me alſo of life. Wee are all the day among ſpies, knives and the apprehenſions of death, which would doe us leſſer harme if it were more ſuddain. Reach out
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:8052:32"/> your aſſiſting hand to the afflicted and grant us ſome ſmall obſcure nook within your Realme, while we expect this te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſt to be blown over; while we wait the dawning of ſome hope, and ſome light of comfort to ſhine againe on our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires: The glory will remaine yours, ours the eternall comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moration of your piety.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Cleopatra</hi> having received theſe Letters, made anſwer without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, and invited her to come down to <hi>Aegypt</hi> with all ſpeed conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, and her ſon with her, telling her that ſhe held it an honour for her to bee able to ſerve for an har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to the afflictions of ſuch a Princeſſe. Departure is fully reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of, but the meanes to contrive it was a piece of difficultie. Poore <hi>Io</hi> knew no way to ſteale her ſelfe away from this <hi>Argus,</hi> who had
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:8052:33"/> ſo many eyes upon her: at laſt (as the wits of women are nimble for inventions, eſpecially in caſes that neerely concern them) ſhee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out imparting her intention to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny body, no not to her daughter <hi>Mariamne,</hi> fearing leſt her too ſoft, and tender nature would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe her to continue ſtill within the bounds of patience, rather then to undergoe ſo dangerous, and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſome a voyage: ſhee (I ſay) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorting the buſineſſe onely to her own fancy, caus'd two Coffins (by an unlucky omen) to be provided for to put her ſelfe and her ſon in; (thinking by this meanes to delude the diligence of the Guard, where in they were to bee conveyed to the ſea-ſide, where lay a Shippe ready to waft them, and ſo to ſave her life through the domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of death. But by misfortune
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:8052:33"/> one of her ſervants named <hi>Eſop</hi> one of thoſe that ſhould have car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the Coffin, going to viſit one <hi>Sabbion,</hi> a man well affected to the houſe of <hi>Alexandra,</hi> hapned to let fly ſome ſpeeches touching this adventure of his Miſtris, as think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hee had talkt to one that was privie to all her ſecrets. Perfidious <hi>Sabbion</hi> had no ſooner pumpt out the whole ſtory from this groom, but he repaires ſtraight to <hi>Herod,</hi> to diſcloſe all that hee had heard, judging this to bee a very expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent courſe for to purchaſe a recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation: for hee was a long time ſuſpected to bee of the faction of <hi>Alexandra. Herod,</hi> when he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved this intelligence, multiplies the number of his ſpies and ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nells. The poore Lady is appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended, and taken out of the Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin (as out of the Sepulchre of the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:8052:34"/> dead, &amp; condemned to live a lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger captivity) all abaſht, &amp; chafing for that the Comoedy ſorted not to a wiſht effect, thinking that (ſince ſhee miſt her ayme) ſhee ſhould not deſire to live any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Yet notwithſtanding <hi>Hered</hi> (whether it was that he feared the great name of <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> or that he would not ſtartle <hi>Alexandra,</hi> that hee might oppreſſe her by ſome more facile way,) did nothing to her for the preſent: He kept cloſe within himſelfe, diſſembling over the matter without ſpeaking one word thereof, though hee ſaw the clouds to gather thick, and ready to burſt into thunder and tempeſt.</p>
            <p>This royall Divell that had rid ſo many ſoules out of the world by Martiall Law, and force of Armes would now ſend away one in ſport. Vpon a day in ſommer,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:8052:34"/> as hee dined with unhappy <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andra,</hi> fayning all that had paſt to be buried in deep oblivion, tells her that in favour of youth, hee would play the young man, and invites <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> his brother in law to play at Racket, or ſome ſuch exerciſe. The match is made, the emulation growes hot, the young Prince being earneſt at his game had not plaid long before he was all in a ſweat, as many other Lords, and Gentlemen were. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold they runne all to the waters, which did glide along neere the place of recreation. <hi>Hered</hi> (who well knew the cuſtome of <hi>Aristo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulus,</hi> and preſuppoſed that hee would not fayle to goe and fling himſelfe into theſe cold bathes,) doth villanouſly complot with ſome youngſters, who (under co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of ſporting) ſhould make him
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:8052:35"/> drinke more water then ſhould ſerve to quench his thirſt. All things ſucceed according as hee had forecaſt. <hi>Aristobulus</hi> ſeeing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the water, ſtrips himſelfe of his cloathes, and beares 'them company, hee had no other intent but to ſwim, play, and skirmiſh on this element, alwaies dangerous, though not ſo treacherous as <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod.</hi> The poore ſacrifice frisks, &amp; leaps, nothing aware of the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune that attended him: But the execrable murtherers knew it wel, foreſpying their opportunity at this fatal ſport, they ſtifle the poor Pontifie under the mercileſſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, being the 18 yeare of his age, and the firſt of his Pontificate. This faire ſun which aroſe with ſuch ſplendor and applauſe, ſets under the waters never to riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain but with the palenes of death
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:8052:35"/> in's viſage. O humane hopes, where, or what be yee? Meere dreames of waking men, aëry phantaſmes of flitting fire, that ſhine only to be extinguiſhed, and in extinguiſhing bereave us of light, leaving us a bad ſtench, and the ſorrow of your loſſe! This Prince in whom was built a new all the hopes, and glory of the roy, all houſe of the <hi>Haſmoneans;</hi> This Prince that ſhould have reunited the Miter, and the Diadem, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived the honour of a race quite extinct, behold him now by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed treaſon ſtifl'd under water, in ſuch an age, and of ſo comely a perſonage, that they made this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident by ſo much the more full of pitty, by how much it was more deſperate of all remedy. At this newes all the City of <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> was in ſuch amazement, as if
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:8052:36"/> 
               <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> being returned from the other world ſtood again before her gates. Every where there was nothing but teares and lamentations, but horrour and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment, out-cries, and the image of death. You would have ſaid that each houſe carried forth to buriall their firſt borne, as had been ſeen long before to fall out in <hi>Egypt.</hi> But above all others <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandra</hi> the pitious mother affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted her ſelſe with ſorrow that would admit of no conſolation: Sometime ſhee bemoan'd, lying proſtrate on the dead corps of her ſon, ſeeking within his eyes (thoſe two ecclipſed luminaries) and on his cold lips for ſome remnant of life: Sometimes ſhe roles her eyes like ſome franticke Prieſteſſe of <hi>Sacchus,</hi> crying for fire &amp; ſword, halters and precipices, that ſhee
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:8052:36"/> might put a period to her life and miſeries! Heavie <hi>Mariamne,</hi> (though the patientſt of all) yet had much adoe to withſtand the violent aſſault of incomparable griefe: ſhee lov'd this brother en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely, as the portrait of her ſelfe, as the diſpoſitary of her heart, as the hope of her houſe too miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly rent, and all wounded with griefe (as ſhe was;) yet (good La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy) ſhe thought of the ſorrows of her mother, and lies behind the dead body of her brother, as if ſhe had been the very ſhadow there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Then turning to God with an affectionate heart ſhe ſends up this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>jaculation.</p>
            <p>
               <q>O my God behold mee now in an eſtate wherein I have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more to feare but thy ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and nothing more to hope for then thy mercies. Hee for
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:8052:37"/> whom I fear'd, and in whom I hop't all that might be fear'd or hopt for in all the events, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of this world is raviſht from me by ſome ſecret decree of thy providence, which I have taught my hart to adore, though the weakneſſe of my apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion cannot trace the footſteps of it. If among ſo many calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, I did yet ſuck any ſweetnes from the world in preſence of this object, which thou haſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaved mee of, loe I am now robd of all; hence for ward, I ſhal finde nothing but worm wood, that ſo renouncing all earthly comforts, I may learne to relliſh thoſe which are proper to thy children reſerv'd in Heaven. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold how pious and gentle ſouls can extract hony out of the rock and turn all to merit even the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtillation
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:8052:37"/> of a teare that trickles down the cheekes. The impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, as <hi>Alexandra,</hi> wound them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves without all conſolation, torture themſelves without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, and ſometimes ſplit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the rock of diſpaire with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out remiſſion.</q>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhall wee ſay that <hi>Herod</hi> too in this ſad conſort of grief did beare his part? He made (indeed) an outward ſhew, and by cloſe hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, did well perſonate a reall mourner. He curſt the ſport, rail'd againſt fortune: He charg'd Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with ſiniſter envy in berea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him of an object, on whom he deſired to expreſſe all the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall love, and reſpect that he bore to the royall houſe, to the which he did (in part) owe his advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>He went to viſit the Queen, and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:8052:38"/> her Mother very ceremoniouſly, and when he beheld them bemoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning about the dead body, the bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh teares guſht out of his eyes: whether it was that he had taught them to drop at command, to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry this diſſembling the more arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficially, or whether indeed he had ſome compaſſion, or pang of grief beholding on the one ſide this ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der flowre, ſo early cut down with deaths impartiall ſickle, together with ſo many celeſtiall graces, which found their period and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon, at the point of their upriſing and nativity; and on the other ſide conſidering the poore Queene drown'd in a ſea of ſorrow, which to behold might force teares from rocks. This perfidious wretch that had ſomething yet of a man, and I believe that nature for that time did extort thoſe teares from
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:8052:38"/> his barbarous cruelty: hitherto he feigned himſelfe to have ſuppreſt his griefe manfully; then turning to the Ladies, tells them that hee was not come then to dry up the flouds of their teares ſo ſoone, which had but too juſt a ſubject to be ſpent upon, himſelfe had not the power to keep back his, he was forc't to give nature leave to haue her courſe, and act her part, time would ſhortly act his too, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply a plaiſter to their griefes; that he would performe in the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the dead Prince as much as an only ſon could expect from an affectionate father, and potent King, and that thenceforth hee would bee the ſon of <hi>Alexandra,</hi> the husband and brother eke of <hi>Mariamne,</hi> ſince God would needs redouble his obligations by the loſſe that they had ſuffered.</p>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:8052:39"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Genuine</hi> Tytanny, what is it but an inſatiable appetite of revenge? <hi>Alexandra</hi> who (a man would think) ſhould have thundred in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious and reproachfull termes, as one that knew well that <hi>Herod</hi> (whatſoever hee put upon it) was author of this Tragoedy, did diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the matter very ſtrongly without ſhewing towards the king on her part, ſo much as a diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented look when time and place would favour her. <hi>Herod</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing himſelfe now from the ſtage, thought hee had acted his part wondrous well, without ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting any ſhadow of ſuſpicion on his ſide, ſeeing that <hi>Alexandra</hi> did not utter a ſyllable, whoſe manner was to pout, and quarrell on farre ſmaller occaſions. To bring in the laſt lenitive, he cauſes the funcralls of the deceaſed Prince to bee cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:8052:39"/> with ſuch pomp, and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence, that nothing more could be added, both for the order, or conduct, and for the rarity of the ſpices, and odours, and alſo for the coſtly ſtructure of the Sepulchre: the ſimpler ſort did verily belieue that this proceeded from a true, &amp; ſincere affection; but wiſer judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſaid they were but feigned teares, or wrung out perforce, and that <hi>Herod</hi> could not be ſad in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt for this accident, which took the mote out of his eye, and did lettle him in full poſſeſſion of the Kingdome of <hi>Iude a. Alexandra</hi> joyning the paſſion of ſorrow with that of vengeance, fayl'd not preſently after funerall rites per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to advertiſe Queen <hi>Cleo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patra</hi> of all that had haphed, and in ſuch dolefull accents, that each period ſeem'd to have beene writ
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:8052:40"/> in teares of bloud. <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> who was already well prepar'd, took fire ſuddenly: ſhee entertaines the matter ſo hotly, as though it had been her own, ſhe gives the alarme to the whole Court, ſhee ſtormes &amp; doth continually laſh the eares of <hi>M. Anthony,</hi> crying, that this was a thing inſupportable, to ſee a forreigner weare a Scepter, that did by no right belong to him, to maſſacre the heyre apparent with ſuch barbarous cruelty, to keep poore Queenes in ſlavery againſt all reaſon, and the priviledge of their births. <hi>Anthony</hi> who knew that <hi>Herod</hi> was his creature, &amp; the work of his own hands, did not willingly give eare to theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints: Nevertheleſſe to ſatisfie <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> he ſwore a ſolemn oath, that hee would examine the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and would ſend for <hi>Herod,</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:8052:40"/> and if he found him guilty of ſuch barbarouſneſſe, he would execute exemplary juſtice upon him. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold <hi>Herod</hi> is ſummoned to <hi>Lao<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicea,</hi> where <hi>M. Anthony</hi> for a time was to ſojourn', hither hee is citee to make his appeara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; to purge himſelfe of the murther of <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulus,</hi> which hee was held to be the author of. This was a crack of thunder to his guilty ſoule, which did terribly awaken him, when he leaſt of all thought of it, &amp; put him in ſuch fearefull dumps, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions that can ſcarce bee i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined. On the one ſide hee had before his eyes the guilt of his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and the voice of blood which cryed loudly in his eares: On the other ſide, hee ſaw that all his fortune did depend on <hi>M. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony,</hi> who would not have ſtirr'd then, but by the inſtigations of
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:8052:41"/> 
               <hi>Cleopatra</hi> his mortall adverſary, &amp; whom hee knew to have had a great longing after the Kingdome of <hi>Iudea</hi> for her own accommoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But nothing tortur'd his braines ſo much as ſome franticke fit of jealouſie, for hee imagined that <hi>Anthony,</hi> a wanton Prince, who went about to obſerve the beauties of Queenes, would have had a taſt of his wife, whoſe pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture had been before brought un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and that for to purchaſe his quietneſſe, he would cauſe him to proſtitute her, as a ſacrifice to his luſtfull pleaſures.</p>
            <p>The man was puzzl'd and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plext on all ſides, and did deſcry every where objects of feare and danger; ſometimes he reſolves on a voluntary baniſhment, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times hee thought it the better courſe to rid himſelfe out of the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:8052:41"/> world, another time he muſters up his wits, and ſtrength, and goes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to make reſiſtance, but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſeem'd better in his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then to delay, and protract the buſineſſe, as much as he could poſſibly. <hi>Anthony</hi> being ready preſt for his expedition againſt the <hi>Parthians,</hi> ſends for him in good earneſt; his delayes, and eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions did improve the former ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicion. He muſt needs travell: or reſolve to looſe all. Hee takes leave of his Mother-in-law <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andra,</hi> and his wife <hi>Mariamne,</hi> without all feare, or complaining, not ſhewing any ſigne of diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, as if he had been tomake a journy only for pleaſure. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, he had yet his own Mother at Court, and his Siſter <hi>Salome,</hi> to whom hee gave ſtrict charge to watch heedfully the ſteps and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:8052:42"/> of thoſe who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he thought had wrapt this web for him. Then taking his unkle <hi>Ioſeph</hi> aſide, hee ſpeakes to him in theſe words; Uncle, you know the buſineſſe which cals me to <hi>Laodicea,</hi> which is indeed of no ſmal conſequence, ſeeing my innocence undermin'd with ſo much ſtudy, &amp; eagernes, and by many powerfull perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, who were the more to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, if their purpoſes could take ſo much effect as it hath of affection. But I hope to break through this miſt, and fowle weather, that you ſhall ſee me triumph over calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny by mine integrity, as you have er'ſt ſeen me triumph over hoſtile attempts by mine Armes: if God diſpoſe of it otherwiſe, all this trouble is procured mee for my beauteous wifes ſake, on who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>M. Anthony</hi> might have ſome plot, &amp;
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:8052:42"/> this might be the occaſion of haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning my journey, for to give his paſſion more eaſe, and liberty. But for the preſent I adjure you by the reſpect you did alwaies beare to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me, by my fortune which you doe reverence, by our bloud and nature, that if (peradventure) you doe underſtand that I bee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe entreated, then my qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and innocence will beare, you permit not after the death of <hi>Herod</hi> that his bed be injur'd. Maintaine the Kingdome for you and yours, and cauſe my wife forthwith to be diſpatcht out of the world, for to beare mee company in another life. Kill her reſolutely for feare ſome take poſſeſſion of her after my death. If ſoules departed have any ſenſe, or ſeeling of the affaires of this world, this will greatly ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and content me.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:8052:43"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was not a litle ſtartled at this tale, yet promiſes notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to put all things in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion according to his will, in caſe neceſſity required it. But his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune alwaies dreadfull, and invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible, made him to conceive farre better hopes: Hereupon hee ſets him on his way, taking with him the choiceſt pieces, and ornaments in his Treaſury for to preſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe, whom he ſhould ſtand in need of: ſhewing moreover ſuch confidence in his countenance, as he harbour'd diſpaire in his heart.</p>
            <p>When he was arrived at <hi>Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cea,</hi> he found many ſtrange infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, &amp; articles drawn againſt him, which did charge him ſorely with the murther of <hi>Ariſtobulus.</hi> It was made manifeſt to <hi>M. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony,</hi> that <hi>Herod</hi> had alwaies his eyes, and thoughts bent upon the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:8052:43"/> kingdome of <hi>Iudea,</hi> ſet on by his furious and exorbitant ambition, ſo that nothing more did check his hopes then to ſee <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> living, to whom hee knew in his conſcience, the Scepter ſo juſtly to belong, that he durſt not beg it himſelfe from the <hi>Romans,</hi> but with the title of Regency, &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectorſhip, during the minority of the right heire. That hee had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted his Regency firſt into a Royalty, then to Tyranny, remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving (as much as poſſibly hee could) the blood Royall from all dignities, for to advance men of naught into ſuch places, witneſſe <hi>Ananel</hi> ſubſtituted to the Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, whereof <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poil'd, that which made him change his purpoſe was not his good will and affection, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, and the apparent danger
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:8052:44"/> which he ſaw to ariſe by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples inſurrection, for the repulſe of the Royall family. That <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtobulus</hi> being promoted to the and receiv'd with the generall ſhouts, and acclamations of the people, this action was ſo diſtaſtfull and odious unto him, that hee could not conceale the madneſſe of his envy, under the mask of his ordinary hypocriſie, that ſince that time he never gave over to perſecute the deceaſed Prince and his mother, in ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manner, that they finding no place of reſt among the living, hid them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the Coffins among the dead, ſo to be convei'd to Sea, and thence to ſaile for <hi>Egypt;</hi> that hee cauſed them to bee apprehended in the fact, and that from thence forward, he ſtudied nothing more then how to rid them out of his
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:8052:44"/> way, that the young Prince died in the waters not ſolitary, &amp; aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned to himſelfe, but ſtifled ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly by ſome inſolent Pages of the Court, and boſome of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this proceſſe, or bill of infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation (ſay they) was ſo evident, and cleare, as if it were written with the Sun-beam. The voice of blood reacht up into heaven, that the Traytor could not ſtill the cry. They ſhew'd the picture of this poore Prince, which was a litle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his death brought into <hi>Egypt</hi> for the ſingular admiration of his beauty, they made his Ghoſt alſo to ſpeak, &amp; to dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d juſtice of <hi>M. Anthony,</hi> for being ſo inhumane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſaſcinned in the flowre and ſpring of his yeares, by the black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt treaſon that ever had been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis'd. The regrets and ſorrows of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:8052:45"/> the poor mother amongſt all theſe were not pretermitted in her ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. <hi>Cleopatra</hi> did act on the Tragoedy, the onſet was hot, the battery very fierce, and violent: <hi>Herod</hi> who never wanted an elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, and ſmooth tongue in his own behalfe, makes his Apology with a moſt demure, and ſober modeſt countenance.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="speech">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Illuſtrious Prince,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>ANd you my Noble Lords that aſſiſt at this Councell, I doe not hold the Scepter of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea</hi> from <hi>Hyrcanus,</hi> nor yet from <hi>Alexandra,</hi> I never had the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to flatter them to this effect, and have leſſe reaſon yet to ſtand in awe of them: You know (moſt noble <hi>Anthony</hi>) that the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome that is now in my hands I hold from you; by you have I
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:8052:45"/> advanced my greatneſſe, and in you are terminated all my hopes. If you command, I am ready at this houre, not to lay downe my Scepter only, but alſo my life, which I was never deſirous to preſerve but for your ſervice: But it troubles mee that the way of death, being wide and open to all the world, that of reputation (which to mee is dearer then my life) is blockt up againſt mine innocence. I am perſecuted by women, and I doe greatly wonder that the ſoule of <hi>Cleopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra</hi> all divine could ingender ſo much choller, and rancor againſt a King, who never fail'd in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects juſtly due to her worth and honor. For <hi>Alexandra</hi> I doe not at all marvell if ſhe rais'd this tempeſt againſt me; her fierce, and high ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit hath ſtill tempted my patience,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:8052:46"/> labouring by all ſiniſter waies to avile, and diſparage my govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to take away perforce a crown, with a more puiſſant hand then thoſe of her fore-fathers hath ſet upon my head. What reaſon could ſhe pretend? Since by the favour of the <hi>Romans,</hi> I doe peaceably ſtand in a Kingdome, which was caſt upon me with the conſent even of my adverſaries. I never ſought for it (my ambition was ſo regular &amp; modeſt) if I had, I had been guilty of a crime ſo hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, that could not come within the thoughts of a mankind-wolfe. There is no man would play the villaine meerly for pleaſure; the Idea of vengeance, which is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the fancie, carries (as it were) a torch before the offence for to reveale it to the world. To what purpoſe had it beene to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:8052:46"/> the life of <hi>Aristobulus?</hi> Was it to eſtabliſh my eſtate? That was ſecure enough already: Your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour (moſt noble PRINCE) hath conferr'd on me more then all ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualities whatſoever ſhall be able to conquer, or raviſh from me. But I have ever put back the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all houſe from all promotions. How put it back? What in calling the disjoynted and ſcattered kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred within my boſome, as much as lay in my power? Every man knowes, how that <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> chiefe of the royall family, being detai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned priſoner among the <hi>Parthians,</hi> I ſtretcht my nerves, bent my veines, and engaged all my credit to ſet him at liberty, and make him returne to Court where he lives now in contented peace, partaking of all the rights, and priviledges of Majeſtie, without moleſting his
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:8052:47"/> head with any care of Civil affairs. 'Tis well knowne I have ſhar'd with him my Crowne, and my bed with his daughter <hi>Mariamne,</hi> making her Queene of Nations, and the ſpouſe of a King. I gave the Pontificate to her brother <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ristobulus</hi> of meere free-will, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no way conſtrained thereunto, as being abſolute in the managing of my eſtate; and if I have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journ'd it for a time, it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the age of the child did not tread equall paces with my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, for in effect they have ſeene him Pontiffie at eighteene yeares of age, which was no ordinary fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. <hi>Alexandra</hi> his Mother which cauſed all this ſtirre and turmoile, ever had full liberty in my Court, except the Licence to undoe her ſelfe, which ſhe ſo oft, and eagerly deſir'd. For what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:8052:47"/> had ſhe to thruſt her ſelfe into a Coffin, and be carried by night as a dead body, to ſteale away out of my Court, and after ſhe had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil'd me in my houſe, now to goe and diſparage me abroad among ſtrangers? If ſhee had deſire to make a journey to Egypt, had ſhe ſpoke the word, it would have ſufficed; but ſhe pleas'd to ſurmiſe falſe dangers in true ſafety, and to put thoſe into hazard of their lives, that made her to live in all ſecurity. When I had diſcover'd this impoſture I have not let out one harſh diſtaſtfull word againſt her, making her to enjoy with caſe the ſpectacle of my patience, and judging that every fooliſh of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender is ſufficiently puniſhed by his owne conſcience. A ſhort time after followed the lamentable death of the young PRINCE,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:8052:48"/> which drew from me bitter teares of compaſſion, for I lov'd him dearly, and I am ſorry his Mother alter'd the ſweetneſſe of his good nature, and caus'd ſo much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his younger yeares. He died not with me, but at his Mothers houſe, and by an accident which no man could prevent; died ſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in the water, an element that we cannot truſt unto, where thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands have periſhed, without any treachery; died with ſome pages of the Court, with whom he did u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually take his paſtime. 'Twas his owne motion that brought him to the water: The alacrity of his youth made him play with dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger it ſelfe, which none could diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him from, and his diſmall fate drowned him. It were too hard, and unreaſonable a taske im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd upon me, if <hi>Alexandra</hi>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:8052:48"/> would have me be accountable for the youthfulneſſe of her ſon, as though I had been his Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, or for the infidelity and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy of the elements, as if I were Lord over them.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This pernicious head delivered this ſpeech with ſuch grace, and plauſibility that hee tooke off the edge of their ſpleene. Such power hath Rhetorick even in the tongue of a miſcreant! Loe he is paſt all danger, being as yet but got abord (as they ſay,) walking in the Court of <hi>Anthony</hi> with all freedome, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting his ſentence of juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. In the meane while (as he was courteous &amp; liberal on occaſions) by vertue of his donatives hee wonne the hearts of the chiefeſt men in the Court, and made all the accuſations to be but the pettiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſpleen of a woman miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inform'd.
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:8052:49"/> inform'd. <hi>M. Anthony</hi> himſelfe told <hi>Cleopatra</hi> that ſhe did ill to intermedie ſo much in forreigne Kingdomes, and if that he ſhould offend by her incitement ſhee might ſtirre up enemies to the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of his eſtate; that <hi>Herod</hi> was a King, and it was not fit to uſe him as a ſubject, nay it was his happineſſe to have him rather for his friend then his foe. While mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were a canvaſing in <hi>Anthony's</hi> Court, the Mother and ſiſter of <hi>Herod</hi> fail'd not to obſerve with all diligent circumſpection the actions of the Queene <hi>Mariamne</hi> and of her Mother <hi>Alexandra.</hi> His Vncle <hi>Joſeph</hi> was Keeper of the Priſon, and did often viſit <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amne,</hi> ſometimes for buſineſſe, and ſometimes for complement. This man began to be ſindged like a butterfly with beames ſhot from
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:8052:49"/> the eyes of this incomparable beauty, and did beare a great deal of affection towards her, and though hee ſaw himſelfe farre e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough from all manner of preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, yet notwithſtanding he took a delight, that hee had plac'd his love on ſo high an object. This paſſion turn'd his braines, and made him fooliſh and talkative, being already clowne enough by ill education, which made him talke wonderfull ridiculous, and fooliſh. For one day when there was a ſpeech made of the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that <hi>Herod</hi> beare to his wife <hi>Mariamne, Alexandra</hi> her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther jeer'd at it very ironically, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to her faſhion; <hi>Ioſeph</hi> who would have the Queene ſtill to entertaine a good liking of her husband his Maſter, whether hee was mad or drunke ſpake with a loud voice:</p>
            <pb n="90" facs="tcp:8052:50"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam,</hi> let your Mother <hi>Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xandra</hi> ſpeak her pleaſure, but to ſhew you an evident teſtimony of the love the King your husband beares you, he gave me a charge, in caſe he were put to death himſelf, to kill you alſo, for that he could not be without your company in the other world.</p>
            <p>At this ſpeech the poor Ladies grew pale and wan with feare. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las the Tyrant (quoth <hi>Alexandra</hi> in her heart) what will hee doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alive, ſince that in his death he cauſeth thoſe to die that ſurvive him. In the mean while there went a rumour very briefe in <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> (the dreames of credulous men) that <hi>Herod</hi> was dead, that <hi>M. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thony</hi> had ſent him to execution, being convicted of the death of <hi>Aristobulus.</hi> Whether this bruite was divulged abroad by ſome of
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:8052:50"/> 
               <hi>Herod's</hi> enemies, or whether him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe made it be ſpread ſecretly, for to prove the countenance and inclinations of men. Wiſe <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anme</hi> ſeem'd to give it no credit. <hi>Alexandra</hi> grew impatient and ſhrudded like a bird on the perch, beſeeching <hi>Ioſeph</hi> with all ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations poſſible to take them out of the pallace, and to lead them to the Court of Guard of the <hi>Roman</hi> legions, committing them into the protection of <hi>Colonel Iulius,</hi> that they might thence paſſe with ſafe conduct to <hi>M, Anthony;</hi> for ſhee greatly deſir'd that this PRINCE might ſee her daughter; perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding her ſelfe that as ſoone as hee ſhould have a view of her, hee ſhould be captivated with her eies, and would ſhew all poſſible favour. Theſe intentions being naughty, had no good ſucceſſe at
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:8052:51"/> all, and all the purſuits of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra</hi> ſerv'd for nothing but to vent her paſſion. <hi>Herod</hi> at length re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnes victoriouſly with authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique teſtimonies of his juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, notwithſtanding all the endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of <hi>Cleopatra:</hi> God reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving this Paracide for a <hi>Cain's</hi> life which concluded with a wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and fearefull death. His mother and ſiſter fail'd not to preſent him forthwith at his arrivall with a modell of their myſtery, and to acquaint him with the intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that <hi>Alexandra</hi> had to put her ſelfe under the power of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans. Salome,</hi> who envy'd <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amne</hi> beyond meaſure, dipping her ſerpentine tongue in the gall of calumnie, accuſed her of ſecret fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity with <hi>Ioſeph:</hi> Wherefore <hi>Herod</hi> who was extreamly jealous, thought inſtantly to cure it, and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:8052:51"/> taking <hi>Mariamne</hi> apart, askt her whence proceeded that amitie which ſhee had contracted with <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> The moſt Chaſt Queen, whoſe patience was never van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſht, ſhew'd by her eies, by the poſture of her countenance, and ſpeeches that ſhee was ſo ſtung with this black ſlander that her <hi>perfidious</hi> husband did eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive how farre ſhe was from ſuch thoughts; and (in truth) being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham'd of himſelfe for propoſing ſuch Queſtions unto her, he crav'd pardon, ſhedding hot tears, and thanking her for proving ſo faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to his bed, and making a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand proteſtations of immortal affection. The good Lady ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what diſpleas'd to ſee ſo much hypocriſie, told him covertly, that indeed hee bare reall love to his wife who would needs have her
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:8052:52"/> company in the other world. <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> preſently apprehended at halfe a word what ſhee meant, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into ſuch diſtemper and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that he ſeemed to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted, tearing his beard &amp; hair, and crying <hi>Ioſeph</hi> had betray'd him, and that now hee muſt needs ſay hee had too much intelligence with <hi>Mariamne;</hi> otherwiſe no man could be ſo ſimple and ſottiſh as to reveale ſo important a ſecret. Hereupon he commands <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to be kill'd outright for a ſacrifice to his returne, not permitting him to come in his ſight, nor would he hearken to one word of excuſe. It did want but a litle that he did not the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fel down more ſacrifices to his wide inſatiate cruelty, and did not put <hi>Mariamne</hi> too to death; but the aſſured proofe of her inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and the impatient heate of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:8052:52"/> his love ſuſpended the blow, that hee might make his anger (like nimble lightning) fly further off, which hee diſcharged on <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra,</hi> whom hee did confine for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>me, keeping her aſunder from Queene <hi>Mariamne</hi> her daughter, taking it now for certaine that it was in her forge that all the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinations, &amp; conſpiracies for his ruine were fram'd and fill'd.</p>
            <p>Not long after, <hi>Herod</hi> ſaw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe imbarkt in another buſineſſe no leſſe dangerous then the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. <hi>M. Anthony</hi> (who ever lent him his ſhoulder to ſupport him) had a long time contended againſt the fortune of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> and was quite diſcomfited in the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell of <hi>Actium,</hi> ending his hopes and life with a ſad Cataſtrophe. This accident aſtoniſht the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant more then can be imagined,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:8052:53"/> ſeeing the prop whereon he lean'd, ruin'd: His affaires which hee thought were now well knit, ripe againe in a night, and had him for an adverſary who was ſo forward in his deſigne for the Empire of the whole world. His friends and foes deem'd him one of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorne hope: He that eſcap't ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhipwracks doth not a whit de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire in this extremity, he takes a reſolution to goe, and find <hi>Caeſar</hi> who was then at <hi>Rhodes,</hi> and to caſt himſelfe at his feet: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſets out on's journey, hee commits one moſt barbarous and inhumane act. <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> the right and lawfull King, who by his gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſſe and facility of nature firſt rais'd <hi>Antipater,</hi> then ſav'd <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod's</hi> life, promoting him to the Kingdome to the prejudice of his owne blood, was yet ſurviving in
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:8052:53"/> a decrepit age laden with yeares &amp; cares: for he was paſt foureſcore yeares. The Tyrant fearing that he alone being left of the Royall blood, ſhould bee reſtored to the throne by the requeſts of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who did tender his innocence, ſeeing him now at the brinck of the grave flings him in, expelling (by brutiſh violence) that ſoule which he was ready to ſurrender up to nature. This was judg'd meer ſavage cruelty without any colour of juſtice, wherewith this abominable monſter ever us'd to palliat his actions: others write the death of <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> to have beene haſtned by this occaſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexandra</hi> (who could not ſhake off her ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but with her skin) ſeeing that <hi>Herod</hi> went on a voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, whence, peradventure, he was never to return, boords her father
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:8052:54"/> 
               <hi>Hyrcanus,</hi> and ſhews him that the time was come wherein God would make his venerable old age to flouriſh anew in Royall purple: The Tyrant is intangled in ſuch nets and labyrinths that hee ſhall never get himſelf out againe. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune knocks at <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> his dore to render him the Diadem which is due unto him by right of inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, and taken from him by tyranny. It remain'd that he would but help himſelfe as much as in him lay, and his good fortune would work out the reſt. <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> replies; daughter the time is come that I ſhould rather meditate on my grave then a Royall Throne. You know what eſteem I made of greatneſſe being yet in an age, and condition when I had all rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to entertaine them, yet I have reno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ac't them with a free-will,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:8052:54"/> preferring my reſt before all the Diadems in the world. Now that I am in the Haven would you have me lanch again into the tempeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Seas: Forbeare ſuch fond ſpeeches (good daughter) I have beheld but too much miſeries, talk to me of a Sepulchre, and not of a Scepter. <hi>Alexandra</hi> replies, that ſince he did not pretend to the life, nor the fortune of the living, yet notwithſtanding that he ought not to neglect his own blood, that he ſhould give way to equity, and he needed not to diſquiet himſelf, but onely to write a few lines to <hi>Malchus</hi> Lieutenant of <hi>Arabia,</hi> and hee would ſupply him with mony &amp; ſufficient forces, as much as he had need of. Laſtly, he was bound in conſcience, and by the law of nature to preſerve his daughter and Grand child from
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:8052:55"/> the teeth of this Tigre. She did ſo ply his eares with theſe &amp; the like reaſons, that at length hee yeelded to her, and treats with <hi>Malchus,</hi> that he ſhould levy for him anum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of horſe. The Letters are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered into the hands of one <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitheus</hi> (a Coſen of this Ioſeph which <hi>Herod</hi> had caus'd lately to be ſlaine) for to be carried withall ſafety; but this perfidious ſlave be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying the blood of his allies, and the fortune of <hi>Hyrcanus,</hi> inſteed of carrying faithfully the Letter to <hi>Malchus,</hi> delivers it into the hands of <hi>Herod,</hi> who bids him go and deliver the ſaid Letter, and bring back the anſwer to him for to diſcover further the counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and intention of the <hi>Arabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</hi> He fail'd not to promiſe <hi>Hyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus</hi> all aſſiſtance, inviting him with all kindneſſe to come over ſpeedily unto him.
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:8052:55"/> 
               <hi>Herod</hi> having diſcover'd the whole matter, calls for <hi>Hyrcanus,</hi> and asketh him if he had received any Letters from <hi>Malchus?</hi> Yea (quoth he) but they contained no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but complements: the other demandes, if with theſe Letters he did not receive ſome preſents? He confeſſed that <hi>Malchus</hi> (indeed) had made him a preſent of foure horſes to draw his Coach. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon without any further forme of proceeding, the Tyrant com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands the reverend old man to be murther'd, dying with blood the hoary head of him who had been his Nurſe, Protector, Father &amp; all. Then after he had cag'd up <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andra,</hi> and <hi>Mariamne</hi> in ſome place of ſtrength under the guard of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> his Treaſurer, &amp; <hi>Soheme</hi> the <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urean,</hi> he goes ſtreight waies towards <hi>Rhodes,</hi> committing the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:8052:56"/> whole charge of his Realme to his brother <hi>Pheroras.</hi> The Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry makes no mention of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Queene and her Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon the death of <hi>Hyrcanus:</hi> Tis credible that all was conceald from them a long time, being kept in cloſe priſon, having no commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication with any body. <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dra</hi> champt upon the bit with much impatience: <hi>Mariamne</hi> did beare out the tediouſneſſe of this captivity with noble conſtancy,&amp; ſought by all meanes to addulce her Mothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s diſcontents. All her comfort was in God, for what elſe could ſhe ſpeak of, or think on? My God (quoth ſhe) thou ſteepeſt all thy creatures for me in worme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood: If I have at any time lov'd them and ſuckt any ſweet from the world, thou gaveſt me for one ounce of Hony a pound of Gall,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:8052:56"/> Ever ſince I lai'd the Diadem on my head, I have felt nothing but thornes, and ſoveraignty was to me but a gorgious and noble ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very. My God, when ſhall we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold that joyfull day to ſhine up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, which wee doe each day wait for, that ſhall dry up our teares, and burſting the bonds of our captivity, ſhall ſend us into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, and into the freedome of thine elect? Theſe poore Ladies remained there in durance among horrid wals with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſeeing any thing but rocks, &amp; wild ſolitude, which ſeemed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſome compaſſion of their griefes: they knew not how the world went, much leſſe how any of the affaires of the Court ſtood: Every time the keeper came to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit them, they expected no other tidings but the doome of death.</p>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:8052:57"/>
            <p>The Guard at the beginning ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome ſeverity in their looks, &amp; were reſerv'd in their ſpeeches, &amp; all ſeem'd full of horrour, feare, &amp; ſad ſilence. But there is no iron but molifies at laſt in the fire. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heme,</hi> viſiting them the oftner ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his commiſſion, felt the rayes that iſſued from <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amnes</hi> eyes ſo ſharp, that they pierc't his heart with relenting compaſſion; judging it too harſh dealing, to detaine a Queene cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, who by the liberall endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which heaven had enricht her perſon with, could captivate all hearts. Hee begins to carry a more benigne aſpect towards her, and <hi>Mariamne</hi> ſeeing him one day in a good mood took occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ſpeak to him with boldneſſe, and to aske him ſome news from the other world.</p>
            <pb n="105" facs="tcp:8052:57"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Soheme</hi> (ſaith the Princeſſe) you ſee us now in a very wofull eſtate, and our perſonages, but a day will come (perhaps) when this tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt will be blown over: misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes doe not alwaies attend at the ſame haven; you know what I am, and that in ſhewing me favour you ſhall not oblige an impotent much leſſe an ingratefull creature: only give us ſome hint of <hi>Herods</hi> purpoſe in deteining us here, and in what caſe the affaires are now abroad. <hi>Soheme</hi> at theſe words felt his heart ſorely ſhaken with a moſT fierce aſſault: on th'one ſide repreſented to his thoughts the revenge of <hi>Herod,</hi> which he obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved lately in the example of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph,</hi> on the other ſide hee was ſo touched with commiſeration at this noble Princeſſe, that this fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen heart began now to melt and
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:8052:58"/> to break forth at his eyes. <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amne</hi> ſeeing him perplext, and at a ſtand: Speak boldly <hi>Soheme,</hi> this ſhall no way prejudice thee being lockt up in deep ſecrecy, &amp; it may doe us much ſervice, for the ſafty of our eſtate. <hi>Soheme</hi> imagining that either <hi>Herod</hi> would never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn in the quality of a King, or that being in the protection of <hi>Mariamne,</hi> hee might eaſily pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe his pardon, unfolds his heart and tells her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Madam</hi> I commit my ſecrets, &amp; life into your power; alſo I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to dye the death before that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver I ſhould come to execute the barbarous command that <hi>Herod</hi> gave me, in caſe the affaires where of hee now treats with <hi>Caeſar,</hi> ſhould not ſucceed according to his expectation. And what was it (quoth Madam) Madam I trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:8052:58"/> only to think on it. 'Tis a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that concernes your life. My friend (replied <hi>Mariamne</hi>) this is his ordinary ſtile: ſo ran the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date to his uncle <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in his firſt voyage. But are there no meanes to get out hence? <hi>Soheme</hi> makes anſwer, that <hi>Pheroras Herod's</hi> bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had charge of the Realme, &amp; that (as extreamly jealous &amp; miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſting) he has a heedfull eye, left by ſome new device you contrive your eſcape. Well, dye then wee muſt (quoth the Princeſſe:) to what ſide ſhall I turne my ſelfe? I ſee nothing but angers and the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of death, with which I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin now to be familiarly acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. <hi>Soheme</hi> comforted her as much as lay in his power; but the ſtopping her eares thence forward to all charmes of worldly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort dilated her heart to receive
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:8052:59"/> ſome from heaven; purifying her vexed ſoule day by day in a Bath of teares, &amp; the ſmarting fornace of her afflictions. O the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Almighty! 'Tis very true what the Scripture ſaith, <hi>Thy paths are in the deep, and thy tracks on the waters,</hi> who can diſcover ſuch dark footſteps! When this moſt chaſt, and innocent Queen in an obſcure priſon ſwimmes every day for a good part of her life in her own teares.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> being imbarkt (as yet all bloody with the maſſacre com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted on the perſon of <hi>Hyrcanus</hi>) findes the Seas and Windes, men and opportunity all propitious to his affaires. This <hi>Proteus</hi> whoſe wit was pliant for all adventures, ſeeing that he could not diſſemble the ſervices hee had done to <hi>M. Anthony,</hi> ſtill proſtrating himſelf,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:8052:59"/> like a fawning Curre at the feet of his fortune, intends to put a faire gloſſe upon them, and cover them with the mantle of vertue. Hee knew that <hi>Augustus</hi> was a Prince well born, generous and juſt, and that hee would employ faithfull ſervants in this new motion of bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſes which he had the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in hand; hee diſguiſeth himſelfe under the ſhadow of vertue, and cheats un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the colour of conſtancy, and pretext of fidelity. Loe now he preſents himſelf to the Emperour &amp; beſpeaks his Highneſſe in theſe tearmes.</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="speech">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Great Emperour,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>BEhold my Perſon and my Crown at your Highneſſe feet; tis reaſon good that all ſhould riſe by your greatneſſe, ſince that God would commit the Empire of the univerſe to your hands. As for me
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:8052:60"/> I cannot feigne, and bely what I have been, no more would I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble what I ought and ſhould be. I haue hitherto ('tis true) ſtood for my noble friend <hi>M. Anthony,</hi> and if he had given eare to mee as he did to <hi>Cleopatra</hi> his Miſtris, you ſhould have found (<hi>Caeſar</hi>) how much I was your enimy, and his friend; but this unhappy Prince being gull'd and beſotted by that creature took money from me, &amp; adviſe from her to ruinate (by ſo doing, his own fortune, &amp; to build yours upon their ruines: I have followed him even to the margen of the grave but did not enter in, in regard my death could no way advantage him; he is in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do nothing but ſend him the tribute of my teares; To you (great <hi>Caeſar</hi>) are due the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices which I do te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der with a fre
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:8052:60"/> &amp; ready heart, if you bee pleas'd to accept of them on the conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not to conſtrain mee to think or ſpeak any thing injuriouſly to the memory of my ancient Maſter, whom being not able to ſerve, I ought nevertheleſſe to reſpect, and love after death.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Augustus</hi> liked well of this bold language, and deem'd that this man was of good proofe &amp; mettle to make a good ſervant of, not ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſubtlety of the Fox, meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all for his own intereſt. He takes the Crown and places it on the head of <hi>Herod,</hi> ſaying, I would you ſhould live peaceably in your dominions, and be but as loyall to me as you have bin to <hi>M. Anthony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> after this ſo lucky an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, ceaſt not to ſet himſelfe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to the good liking of <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus,</hi> ſeeking all occaſions ſo to do,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:8052:61"/> but moſt of all in that voyage of the Emperour made to <hi>Aegypt,</hi> where he did continually give aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance and ſerve in many good offices. This buſineſſe ſo happily ſped, hee returnes in triumph to <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> with the aſtoniſhment of all the world. This was it that the vertuous Queen <hi>Mariamne</hi> did protract a life for ever to bee a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for the ſolemnity of her bloody husbands triumphs.</p>
            <p>Let us now ſee how this Lamp was extinguiſht, we cannot expect any ill ſent, the faire qualities of her life did accompany her to her death. Aſſoon as <hi>Herod</hi> was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred within the chief City, he goes to ſalute the Queen his wife whom he had cauſed to be ſet at liberty, being his affaires were in ſafety, &amp; brings her the firſt tidings of the happy ſucceſſe of his voyage, hee
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:8052:61"/> was ſo ſwolne with the conceit of his good fortunes, that hee could hardly contain himſelfe within his skin, and the loue of ſo amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble an object as was then preſent after ſo many dangers exhauſted, did let his tongue looſe to much boaſting &amp; vain ſuperfluous ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, thinking that by his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe he did much improve his honour and reputation. <hi>Mariamne</hi> pin'd away upon her leggs with fretfulneſſe to heare his vanities, and as ſhe was free and genuine in all her carriage, ſhee ſhewed how litle pleaſure ſhe took in his Rho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domantades, which his joy did heighthen to a degree of folly. He imagining this at firſt to bee but a fit of Melancholy which would ſoon vaniſh into ſmoak, did chear her up the more with words, ſhewing more Court-ſhip then
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:8052:62"/> uſuall. Among theſe careſſes, the poore Lady breathes out a ſigh or two, calling to minde the ſecret command lately given to <hi>Soheme.</hi> He well perceived by her counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance that ſhe was ſomewhat diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented, and entred into a ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that <hi>Soheme</hi> alſo had the flux in the tongue as well as <hi>Ioſeph.</hi> He knew not then how to compoſe his countenance, ſo much was hee moved within himſelfe. Love, choler, and jealouſie did inceſſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hurry, and diſquiet him: hee could not be angry as he would, &amp; could not chooſe but love whom he had ſtill impotently lov'd. This haughty ſpirit that could never ſtoop to any, but to deceive, was aſham'd to ſee himſelfe thus diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arm'd, and become as it were a Zanie in amorous dalliances not ordinary to his nature; then ſeeing
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:8052:62"/> that theſe ſubtilties did not ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, hee torments himſelfe the more, and thinks now to flouriſh with the ſword, but love was ſo predominant over wrath, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held the ſtroak: Hereupon he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tires, ſhaking his head, and mutte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring I know not what between his teeth, as curſing that love which made him mercifull in deſpight of his inclination. But alas there is no hatred to that of wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt their own kinde, when a jealouſie once ſeiſeth on their braines! <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre</hi> an <hi>Arabian</hi> by nation, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Herod,</hi> &amp; <hi>Salome</hi> his ſiſter, ſeeing him ſo paſſionate fayled not to blow the coales with their tongues, and to kindle them with impudent ſlanders which the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant gave credit to in part, but yet could not reſolve to ſtrike the ſtroak. It was a long time in agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:8052:63"/> ere any thing could be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded upon; at laſt there arives an unhappy day, when at noone-tide having withdrawn himſelfe to his privy chamber he ſends for <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riamne,</hi> who preſently comes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the meſſage: But <hi>Herod</hi> being minded to a game in bed, ſhee would not conſent thereto, telling him the law of nature forbad her to lye with a man that had mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd her Father and her Brother, meaning <hi>Alexander,</hi> who by the perſuit of <hi>Herod</hi> had been over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown by the <hi>Romans,</hi> and her brother <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> ſo cruelly ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled in the waters. Here <hi>Ioſephus</hi> the Hiſtorian, after hee hath ſo highly extol'd <hi>Mariamne</hi> as a chaſt Queen and truly endowed with an inviolable faith (for theſe be his words) taxes her with a litle diſdain which was (as hee ſaith)
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:8052:63"/> grown up with her nature, in that ſhee did diſreſpect the careſſes of her husband. But hee that would well ponder how <hi>Herod</hi> had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated her neereſt kindred, maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cring them moſt indignly, &amp; how that holding the Scepter from her houſe hee did not eſteem of her as of a Queen, but as of a poore vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctime, which he caus'd to be ſhut up, commanding it to be beheaded whenſoever he ran in jeopardie of his life, for feare that any other ſhould enjoy her after his death; he ſhall finde that the Lady had ſufficient reaſon to give him this anſwer. Nevertheleſſe <hi>Herod</hi> that could not brook ſuch freedome of ſpeech, was ſo incens'd at theſe words that he went neere then to doe her a miſchiefe; his eyes ſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kling with anger, his voice rough, and his hands lift up to commit vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence.
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:8052:64"/> As he walkt up &amp; down in his chamber in a chafe, skirmiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus with his choler, <hi>Mariam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne</hi> ſtanding by without any far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reply, treacherous <hi>Salome</hi> thought it now a convenient time to give vent to her malitious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; ſhee ſends a ſervant that had pawn'd his faith and credit, and whom ſhe a long time had been inſtructing for to make him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a ſlander as wicked as ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, which was, that <hi>Mariamne</hi> having an intention to giue her husband a philtre (or love potion) ſhe addreſt her ſelfe to him, who being then the Kings Taſter and ſought to work him to doe this feat with many rewards, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, which he would never give care unto. Moreover hee was ſo taught his leſſon, that if, peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>Herod</hi> demanded the ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:8052:64"/> of the Philtre, hee ſhould anſwer without farther heſitation that the Queen had the contriving of it, and that ſhe required of him only but to adminiſter it. This mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcreant enters the chamber in cold bloud, and makes depoſition moſt ſeriouſly: whereat <hi>Herod,</hi> who was all fire already, being more inflam'd then ever, thought with himſelfe that he needed not won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any more whence this impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of love ſhould proceed. Hee commands preſently an Eunuch of the Queen, one of the moſt tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of them to be attacht, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that nothing paſt without his knowledge, hee puts him to the rack, inſomuch that his body be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing already weak enough, not able to beare out the violence of the tortures, and on the other ſide ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving nothing to ſpeak againſt his
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:8052:65"/> good Miſtris, in whoſe converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he never knew any thing but what was honourable and honeſt; hee was kept a great while in this miſerable plight, at length hee lets fly a word, ſaying that hee had ſeen <hi>Soheme</hi> talking a long time in private with the Queen, as though hee made ſome diſcovery and that ſince that time hee well perceived that ſhe was much deje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. <hi>Herod</hi> had no ſooner heard this ſpeech, but 'tis enough, ſaith he, take him off and call <hi>Soheme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Soheme</hi> knew nothing of this that paſſed, he liv'd in great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, having lately attain'd to ſome good place of command by the Queens recommendation. He was quite aſtoniſht when he ſaw them lay hands on him and compell him to confeſſe the diſcourſe hee had with <hi>Mariamne</hi> when ſhe
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:8052:65"/> was in priſon: he utterly denying the matter is forthwith ſlain. This day <hi>Herod</hi> retires into his Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, drinking by full draughts the gaul and venome of his fatall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, meditating in his heart on the fury which hee ſhould make to burſt out ſhortly in publique: for without allowing any truce to his labouring brain, he aſſembles his Privie Councell, and ſends for his Queen, who exprected nothing leſſe then ſuch arraignment. This monſter that ſtudied alwaies to ſet a colour of juſtice on his moſt unreaſonable actions, beginnes a long Oration which he had indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at his leaſure, and as every man ſtood like a Ghoſt ſtruck with feare and filence, expecting the iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue of this Tragoedy (onely bold <hi>Mariamne</hi> ſtood arm'd with an undanted conſtancy for all events)
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:8052:66"/> he ſpeaks to them in theſe termes.</p>
            <p>It ſeems God would counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ballance my proſperous affaires a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad with the unhappineſſe of domeſtick evills: I have found ſafety among the winds and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts in irkſome voyages I have undertaken, and in many perillous atchievements that I have brought about, to finde in my return a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt in mine own Court. You are not ignorant how that I have fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered all the houſe of <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> in my boſome in thoſe deplored times, when it was at a low ebb, &amp; neer confuſion; in recompence whereof as if I did ſit upon the egs of a Serpent, ſo I have found but hiſſing and ſtinging. God knowes how oft I have diſſembled inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and how oft I have cur'd the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with patience, but yet I cannot bring my heart to ſo obdurat and
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:8052:66"/> brawnie a temper, but it is ever &amp; anon ſtirr'd up and ſcarified with ſome new ſores. Behold there my wife, who following his Mothers ſteps, is ever bent to trouble my repoſe. As ſoon as I was return'd from my late dangerous voyage, as you know, I brought her ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the happy ſucceſſe to my affaires, ſhee ſhewing how litle e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem ſhe made of my eſtate and perſon, did heare mee with ſuch a coy and diſdainfull carriage, that notwithſtanding all the Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip I made to her, I could not draw from her pride one good word, nay ſhee was not content with this, ſhee proceeds to open miſchiefes, and bloudy machina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which I had rather (in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of your eares) paſſe over in ſilence, &amp; come to effects. Behold there one of my faithfull ſervants,
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:8052:67"/> that doth teſtifie how that ſhe had ſuborn'd him to give me a Philtre, that is, poyſon for to giddie my braines, and take away my life, which God doth ſtill preſerve to make a recognizance of all the good offices which all in generall and you in particular have done me: So you ſee that I am arrived home with my temples girt with Laurells, honoured and favour'd by the moſt renowned men of the world, to bee the ſhittle-cock of a womans mallice, and the But of her treachery. I could not win her by ardency of love, or any good turnes, no more then if ſhee had been a Lioneſſe. Conſult among you what you ought to doe, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver her to the power of your iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, being not (in this caſe) to follow mine own judgement, that poſterity may know that mine
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:8052:67"/> own intereſts come alwaies below the truth, to which I have taught them ever to ſtoop and bend the knee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> in ſpeaking theſe words would ſeem to be very calme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juring down his paſſion, and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing his nature which was pliable enough, but yet his choler ſo wrought and fum'd up, that the Councell ſoon diſcover'd his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lady, &amp; that he had a full purpoſe to exterminate the Queen. They ſummon her to anſwer upon the ſuddain without any Advocate. This glorious <hi>Amazon,</hi> a young Impe of the <hi>Macchabees,</hi> and heire of their heroick patience, being preſented before this crue &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticle of malignant ſpirits, 28 yeares before the comming of our Saviour in the fleſh, did then what may inſtruct poſterity moſt
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:8052:68"/> illuſtriouſly by her example. No man ever obſerv'd an impatient word to ſally out of her mouth, ſhe uſed not any word of recrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, or charged back any with their own crimes, and being able to lay before the Councell the many outrages ſhe had ſuffered in her own perſon, and in her kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, ſhe ſwallowed all wrongs with more then humane patience only touching the main Article of her accuſation, ſhe ſaid that for the draught or potion that was obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to her, 'twas a thing in the judgement of all that would confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it well, fartheſt off any thing from her thoughts, ſeeing that ſhe had alwaies dreaded the love of <hi>Herod</hi> more then his hate: moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver that ſhe made not any account of her life wherein ſhe had endur'd but too many afflictions, much
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:8052:68"/> leſſe of the Court where ſhe never drew any ayre of delight, and that if they would oppreſſe her inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence by falſe witneſſe, it was moſt eaſie to overcome her, no ſubject more obvious and probable. It was moſt eaſie to take the Diadem off her head and her head off her ſhoulders, but it would bee no eaſie taske to take from her the reputation of a Lady of Honour which ſhe held in <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite</hi> from her anceſtors, &amp; which ſhe would carry along with her to the duſt.</p>
            <p>The poore ſoule was as a filly Lamb in the jawes of a Lion, and in the fangs of many Wolues: They proceed to judgement and all proceed according to <hi>Herods</hi> propenſion. They knew it was his will to rid her out of his way, that was ſufficient. There was not one
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:8052:69"/> found that had the boldneſſe to ſtand up in the defence of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Queen, or to aſſwage the paſſion of <hi>Herod</hi> in any manner. Each mans conſcience was clog'd either with crimes, or timorouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; whence it hapned that theſe impious judges did more in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of the Tyrant then he would have done, for they all concluded to adjudge her to death: hee was ſtruck with ſome horrour at the firſt, as bloudy a man as he was, &amp; commanded that ſhee ſhould bee committed to ſafe cuſtody within the Court, ſuſpending the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, thinking perhaps thereby to make her the more tractable to his humour. But enraged <hi>Salome</hi> that had ſtirr'd up this tempeſt not willing to leave a thing halfe done drawes neere to the King her bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; makes remonſtrance, that
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:8052:69"/> ſuch birds were not to be kept in cages that this was a buſineſſe which concern'd his Crowne and Life, and that all now tended to a revolt, if he delai'd this execution he would haſten his owne ruine and the eſtates both: whereupon <hi>Herod</hi> let ſlip this ſpeech, <hi>Why let ber be taken away;</hi> and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately a Tribune was diſpatcht, to the good Queene, who brings her news of her laſt houres approach, ſaluting her with all reverence, <hi>Madam</hi> the King calls for you, and you are preſently to die: ſhe nothing moved with the meſſage replies, let us goe (friend) outright, <hi>Herod</hi> cannot be ſo ſpeedy but he ſeemes ſlow to me: and when ſhe had thus ſaid ſhee advances for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and marches ſtreight to the place of execution, without chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging her colour, with a cleer coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:8052:70"/> which drew tears from all ſpectatours to crowne her pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. As ſhe was ready to receive the fatall ſtoake, <hi>Alexander</hi> a her Mother, her companion in Priſon, the Cabinet of her thoughts, that both ſeem'd to have but one heart intwo breaſts betraying her blood, nature, and all pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie for ſome miſchievous reaſon of eſtate that ſhe might not be ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected of <hi>Herod</hi> as though ſhe had conſented to her daughters per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſneſſe, comes there to taxe her with horrible injuries, and ſhee went neere to dragge the poore Princeſſe by the haire of the head, and to hale her along the pave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, telling her in extreme rage, that ſhe was an untoward peeviſh dame, and that ſhee did well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve death for that ſhe would not agree with ſo good a husband for
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:8052:70"/> the ſupporting of their common fortunes. See here the greateſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignity that can be conceived! In ſuch an accident there is no better hony, nor a worſer ſting then that of bees, and no better amity, nor worſer enmity then that of kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred. Patient <hi>Mariamne</hi> did not ſpeake a word, not ſo much as, Good Mother permit my ſoule to depart in peace which is now up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my lips ready to take her flight, and trouble not my laſt and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall reſt; but with a generous ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence ſealing her mouth to all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, and opening her heart to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God the only witneſſe of her innocence, being thus indign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly handled, ſhee profers her neck to the headſman for to ſeale with her blood the laſt teſtimonies of her patience. <hi>Ioſephus</hi> ſpeakes not ſo expreſſely of the manner of her
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:8052:71"/> death as being a matter without controverſie that ſhee was execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted according to the ordinary manner of thoſe times, which was to behead all delinquents of ſuch ranke. This faire breaking of the day which as yet carried com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and healing in his wings to the poore afflicted ſoules that were in this horrible confuſion of Tyranny, was then obſcur'd and quite put out with her blood: the eyes of all the throng that did aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt at this ruefull tragedie being bath'd in teares did behold her in her red lips. When they ſaw this countenance (arm'd with royall Majeſty) ſo couragiouſly to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front death which makes the boldeſt heart to tremble, and her alabaſter neck ſtretcht out and ſtoop't to the glittering axe to be ſever'd from her faire body, a
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:8052:71"/> cold horror ran through the ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering joynts, and bones of all the croud, and there was no rock ſo hard but would have ſweated wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try drops of teares to ranſome her blood from being ſpilt. Her head was ſever'd from her body, and her body from her ſoule, but this will never be ſeparated from her God, who rears to her memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry an eternall trophie of patience. Her trunck lay cold, and extended upon the place, and the voice of innocent blood, which now mounted up to pierce the Clouds, &amp; demand revenge from the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector of innocence, was incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently heard to good purpoſe, as you ſhall e're long underſtand.</p>
            <p>This faithleſſe husband that had ſo barbarouſly handled a Princeſſe ſo worthy of all reſpect, was ſoone as ſhe had yeelded up
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:8052:72"/> the ghoſt as if he had been ſtruck with an inviſible dart, cryed out of griefe, and ſai'd that he had given a blow that deſerved God's an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger &amp; vengeance; then with fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full howling he invokes inceſſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the memory and name of the deceaſed Queene, to whom hee could not by his plaints reſtore what he had taken away by the executioners hatchet: whither ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he went, he was ſtil accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with the Image of his crime; black furies revelling in his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, &amp; terrifying him with ſights and fearfull apparitions: hee tried all manner of feaſting, dancing, and delights to expell melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; but it encreas'd the more, in ſo much that he was conſtrained to abandon the helme of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, though hee had been active and indefatigable in this exerciſe:
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:8052:72"/> he became at firſt a dotard, and all ſtupid, not knowing what hee did; for ſometime at dinner he ſpeakes to his attendants, and bids them call the Queene to him, as if ſhee had been ſtill alive, they hearkned unto him without returning a word, &amp; all the Court was ſtruck with ſilence and amazement; at laſt he being not able to endure the pallace walles, as though they did upbraid his cruelty, hee goes and haunts the groves &amp; uncouth places of retreate like a ſalvage, thereby contracting ſuch a ſtrange diſeaſe in his braines, and ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent a frenzy, that the Phyſitians ſaw no way to remedy it, telling him freely that it was a blow from heaven: God who did reſerve him for further calamities would not vouchſafe to take away his life at that preſent. That wicked Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:8052:73"/> 
               <hi>Alexandra</hi> that ſo outragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſſly ſcolded at her daughter on the ſcaffold, went ſhortly after the way of all fleſh, taſting the bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of death but looſing the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of it. In the reare of this, followed a peſtilence which ſwept away many of <hi>Herod's</hi> counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors of ſtate; and all theſe were but the ſcourges of heaven to avenge this ſo lamentable death, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver enough lamented. <hi>Mariamne</hi> from her chaſt bed left <hi>Herod</hi> two ſonnes, <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtobulus</hi> who were very young, capable to endure much more in after-times, but as then incapable to underſtand their preſent miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. <hi>Herod</hi> for to take away from them the reſentments of this hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid fact, and to raiſe them both to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by good education to the glory of his Scepter, packs them
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:8052:73"/> away in good time, and ſends them to <hi>Rome</hi> to be train'd up in <hi>Auguſtus Caſar's</hi> Court, held at that time the Academy of Kings, and the moſt renowned School of the world. After ſome years ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pir'd he tooke a deſire to make a journey into <hi>Italy</hi> for to ſalute <hi>Caſar,</hi> and by that meanes to ſee his ſonnes, whom hee found very well improv'd, and ingeniouſly brought up, and ſo compleat, that hee would faine with the good leave of <hi>Auguſtus</hi> bring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> along with him back to <hi>Iudea,</hi> and ſo he did: Theſe young Princes retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> with <hi>Herod,</hi> did raviſh all the people with admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration; they were of a very come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proportion very nimble and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, and well exercis'd in feats of armes, well ſpoken, affable, and as much worthy of love as their
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:8052:74"/> Father of hatred. Men beheld them as they doe the two ſtarres of <hi>Castor</hi> and <hi>Pollux</hi> after a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt; they fill'd all with joy, and ſeem'd already to have wonne hearts enough to winne them crownes according to their merit, yet thoſe that call'd to mind the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of their Mother <hi>Mariamne</hi> could not containe their teares.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pheroras, Herod's</hi> brother, and his ſiſter <hi>Salome,</hi> who had both of them a hand in the murther of the innocent Queene, entred into ſuch apprehenſions that cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt, ſeeing that the blood which they had ſpilt was one day to rule over them: They began thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth tartly to traduce them, and convey (by ſome creatures ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born'd thereto) many reports to <hi>Herod's</hi> cares, which were in effect to informe, how that the Princes
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:8052:74"/> his ſonnes (in regard of what had hapned touching their mother) were very averſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their Father, &amp; would never beinduced to affect him againe. <hi>Herod</hi> who was yet warm with the heat of his affection towards the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, gave no credit to the ſlander; for ſeeing them now upon the march towards ripes yeares, he bethought him how to match the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> honourably, ſueing for his ſon <hi>Alexander</hi> the daughter of <hi>Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus</hi> King of <hi>Capadocia</hi> named <hi>Glaphira,</hi> which was granted him, &amp; for <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> he was betrothd to the daughter of <hi>Salome,</hi> his coſin <hi>Germane;</hi> thus cementing the breaches &amp; enmities of his houſe. <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Aristobulus</hi> did converſe together very freely, and ſpoke all that lay upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their hearts, talking of the death of their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in ſuch a manner, that they
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:8052:75"/> ſhewed that they were ſenſible of it: <hi>Pheroras,</hi> and <hi>Salome</hi> very cloſe and malignant ſpies, did not ceaſe to toll them into dangerous ipee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and all that they had ſpoken (either through vanity, or ſome fit of anger, or through preſumption of ſecrecy) was preſently reported to <hi>Herod's</hi> eares. Crafty <hi>Salome</hi> yet beating ſway over her new married daughter, who was a ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple harmleſſe creature, did ſhrife her punctually, to know of her what her husband did uſe to talke of in the privacy of their mutuall embraces. Shee forth with related all the ſpeeches, which theſe poor Princes had ſpoken in ſimplicity or merriment, namely, that <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtobulus</hi> brag'd, that the Empire appertain'd to the iſſue of <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amne</hi> as the linage of a true Queen: as for the ſonnes of <hi>Herod,</hi> they
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:8052:75"/> were ſow'd abroad, and diſperſed in good number (for hee had ſome nine or ten wives) ſo that he made moſt of them advocates in petty Townes, and it went well with them if they had learn'd to read and write; ſhee added moreover, that <hi>Alexander</hi> ſpake in a <hi>bravado,</hi> that he was ſomewhat of another mold then his Father, yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding when hee convers'd with him, ſeeing him of a jealous hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour he kept himſelfe within his ſcabbard, not daring freely to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe himſelfe, for fear of caſting ſhadowes of his ability; that going to hunt, and walke with <hi>Herod,</hi> he us'd to contract and wind in his body, that he might not ſeem big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then his father: If he went to draw a bowe, hee did it very bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gler-like, of purpoſe to free him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from all envy. This was a
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:8052:76"/> maine peece of wiſdome to doe ſo, but the trick of a very novice to talk ſo much, though words as innocently ſpoken, as ſiniſterly and captiouſly interpreted; and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all a very ſimple errour, to commit their ſecrets to a woman, whoſe breſt (for the moſt part) is as fit to guard any thing intruſted to its cuſtody, as a five to carry water. When <hi>Pheroras,</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lome</hi> had diligently plyed the ears of <hi>Herod</hi> with theſe petty infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, ſeeing ſome ſuſpition to plant, &amp; take rooting in his mind, and that the fathers affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his ſonnes did waxe cold, they ſtrike in opportunely, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe him ſeriouſly to take heed of his ſons, that they were in labour with ſome great exploit, and ſpake loudly, That all thoſe that had any hand in the ſhedding their mothers
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:8052:76"/> blood, ſhould not beare the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment off in the other world: For indeed as they were harping on that harſh ſtring, ſuch like ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches did eſcape from them. <hi>Herod</hi> was exceedingly aſtoniſht at this freedome, as thinking it neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to repreſſe their boldneſſe with ſome counterpriſe. What doth he to take downe the ſpirits of theſe Princes? Hee goes, and takes him one of his other ſonnes call'd <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipater,</hi> (begot upon one <hi>Dorid</hi> a woman of meane ranck, and who was afterward ſhamefully baniſht the Court) he hoiſts him in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the top of the wheele, not that hee purpos'd to leave him there, but hee would have him ſerve as a Check-mate for the ſons of <hi>Mariamne,</hi> judging him a fit inſtrument for that end: For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed this <hi>Antipater</hi> was a darke,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:8052:77"/> ſullen, and malicious ſpirit, who held much after the Father. When he ſaw himſelfe on an inſtant ſo highly mounted, he reſolv'd not to deſcend, but with the loſſe of his skin, &amp; to ſhare of the Realm as well as the reſt, by ſome device or other. Well, to that end he fits the Scene, and conforms himſelfe to all faſhions for to get into cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit with <hi>Herod,</hi> (who from that time began to like him very well) and he fail'd not under hand to put on foot afreſh thoſe accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to get ſurer footing in this new preferment, that had been commenced againſt the ſonnes of <hi>Mariamne.</hi> And when hee had flung the ſtone, he drew in his arm ſo neatly, that hee ſeem'd not to have any way ſtirr'd in it; for he did alwaies bear a moſt reſpectful carriage towards <hi>Alexander,</hi> and
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:8052:77"/> 
               <hi>Aristobulus,</hi> as towards his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, eſpcially when hee caus'd thoſe falſe reports to be inſtill'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh into his Fathers eares, by ſome creatures well taught and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded. He fain'd alſo, with a bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed modeſty to take their cauſe in hand, but hee excuſed them ſo ſlily to his own advantage, that he brought them within greater ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicion then before. King <hi>Herod</hi> for to bring him into ſome eſteem and authority, thought it were not amiſſe to ſend him to <hi>Rome</hi> for a time, which he did, giving him a flouriſhing attendance, and an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite deale of recommendations. Here hee ſate a brooding more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genious miſchiefs, &amp; from hence purſued his plots more cloſely, &amp; with more art. In a letter to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, hee wrote that he had diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered at <hi>Rome</hi> ſtrange plots, that
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:8052:78"/> he ſhould beware of his brethren, <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Ariſtobulus;</hi> for they had every where ingroſſed the hearts of the people, and that their deſigne was no other, then to ſhorten his daies, &amp; to diſpoſſeſſe him of his kingdome. This had the more colour, for that the yong Princes being not a litle moved with their late rejection or degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation could not diſſemble their diſcontents, and did dayly caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſome words, which were ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd up by the ſpies of <hi>Pheroras,</hi> and <hi>Salome,</hi> that no fillable fell to the earth. It griev'd <hi>Herod</hi> to ſee that having compos'd all in peace abroad, the fire had caught hold on his own houſe: and thence for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward he had a minde to ſeize up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his ſonnes, but hee would not make any attempt upon their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons without <hi>Caſars</hi> command, to
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:8052:78"/> whom he referr'd all, both for the expreſſion of his obeiſance, and for the ſafety of his eſtate. After he had meditated on the matter with himſelfe very carefully and ſeriouſly, (for it did much grieve his heart whence all his Counſels did ſpring, &amp; had their firſt riſe,) he reſolv'd to bring his ſonnes to <hi>Rome,</hi> &amp; there to accuſe them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Caeſar.</hi> All along the way fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Paleſtine</hi> to <hi>Italy,</hi> did hee carry his thoughts ſo cloſe, that his lookes did never betray them, nor did he ſhew any ſymptoms of diſtaſt to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Sonnes, leſt hee ſhould caſt ſome ſhadowes of ſuſpition. Being arriv'd at <hi>Rome,</hi> hee under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands that <hi>Caeſar</hi> was then in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilegia,</hi> whither hee poſts with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay, bringing his two ſons along, who were by the Emperor (who was as a father to them) ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:8052:79"/> courteouſly received with all demonſtrations of affection. In the interim this wretched father, eſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his opportunity begges from <hi>Caeſar</hi> a day of audience, in a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (as he ſaid) of great conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, which he granted him, &amp; he came upon the very inſtant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon, bringing with him the two delinque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, who intended no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing as then, but to laugh, &amp; paſſe the time with their old acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. When they were in the midſt of a glorious aſſembly (which were of purpoſe there met) <hi>Herod</hi> fetching a deep ſigh, addreſſeth his ſpeech to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour.</p>
            <p>You now behold (<hi>Great Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi>) a King happy enough by your Grace, and favour, but a moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Father in the diſgraces, &amp; ill fortunes of my houſe: if nature
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:8052:79"/> had deni'd me iſſue, fortune would haue ſav'd me much miſery, and trouble. It doth much grieue mee to ſoile your eares (renowned <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi>) with the recitall of ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graciouſneſſe; but neceſſity which hath no law compels me, &amp; your juſtice which protects all Lawes, invited me to it. Loe here my two Sonnes (unnaturall Sons) who had the honour to bee brought up at your feet, after that they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd from mee all favour, that might be expected from a king by your goodneſſe potent enough, &amp; from a father by his own nature moſt indulgent, betraying the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of their education received at your hands, and forgetting their bloud and nature receiv'd from me, they have attempted a crime which I am afraid to utter. I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured much for them, add their
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:8052:80"/> welfare, and I enjoy a kingdome now a faire terme of yeares, which I have purchas'd with ſo much ſweat, and turmoile; I have ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the gate of honour for them to enter at after my deceaſe, when a naturall death ſhould cloſe up mine eyes; but they would needs enter in at the gate of paricide, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ambuſh for my life, for to take away the ſpoile ſoakened in my bloud. I haue them here at your feet, not retaining in mine own wrongs any right of a King, or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but what your juſtice will think fit to ordaine, and preſcribe: Yet (<hi>Creat Caeſar</hi>) I muſt beg of you this requeſt, that you would grant my old age, which you have ſo much honoured, ſome reſt in mine own houſe, &amp; to reſcue me from the hands of theſe Paricides. Alſo I doe not think it any way
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:8052:80"/> expedient, that ſuch graceleſſe, &amp; ungratefull Sons, that have trod under feet the Laws of God and men, ſhould any longer look the Sun in the face, which ſhould both witneſſe, and upbraid their folly.</p>
            <p>The man ſpake this with won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull vehemency, ſo that he did amaze all the aſſembly; and the poor youths which had as much innocence, as ſimplicity, ſeeing themſelves thus battered, &amp; over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne with a tempeſt of words, which they did never preſage, made their eyes to weep an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, &amp; they fall a crying in good earneſt: they ſtrove to recover their ſpeech, fearing that their ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence would prove them guilty; but the more they labour'd to vent their thoughts, the more did their ſobs interrupt their courſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Augustus Caeſar,</hi> a judicious and
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:8052:81"/> humane Prince, ſaw well by their demeanour, and countenance, that the young men were guilty of more miſery, then miſchiefe, and caſting a gracious look upon them Courage my Youths, ſaith hee to them, ſtand firme, anſwer all by leaſure, let nothing diſmay, or trouble you. All the Court did now pitty them, and <hi>Herod</hi> too ſhew'd in his countenance, that he was a litle mov'd; ſo eloquent are our naturall ſtrength and armes <hi>Alexander</hi> ſeeing the eyes of all to caſt propitious, and favourable beames upon them, wakens his ſpirits, and breaking through a throng of ſighs (as he was pretty well tongu'd) he ſpake as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: My Lord and Father, your Majeſtie hath not (I truſt) brought us ſo far before the Altars of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, for to make us a ſacrifice to
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:8052:81"/> vengeance; wee are at the knees of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> as in the temple of clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, whither being conducted by your conſent, &amp; command, I muſt needs ſay, that as your words were rough, and bitter, ſo are your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings moſt faite and gentle. If calumnie could have ſo altered your good nature, as to have wrought you to aſſaile our lives, to the diſadvantage, and hazard of our innocence, this you might have done in <hi>Palestine,</hi> as a Father, and as a King, the doome and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution was in your own power: but God permitted it, that you have led us to the court of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> not to leave our heads here, which you have deſtinated to a Crowne, but to bring them backe victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly triumphing over detractio. It is a ſtrange thing, to invent ſo erroneous a crime againſt perſons
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:8052:82"/> of our quality &amp; reputation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out alleaging why, or how. Here is no ſpeech of any letters, poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, complots, treacheries, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſubom'd to practiſe them, only we are proclaim'd Paricides, and the proofes left behind, not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny produc'd: if this ſufficeth, there will not be found ſuch exalted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence in the world, which ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der wil not dare to faſten his teeth upon. Our enimies, who of a long time have been weaving this web, ſay nothing, but that we have age and courage enough to performe this, &amp; that we would one day at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to avenge our Mother <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riamnes</hi> death. As for the firſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, who ſees not how weak it is? If there needs but age, &amp; courage to commit a murther, this were to make the whole ſurface of the world a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelm
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:8052:82"/> it with a deluge of bloud; to make all parents jealous, &amp; mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſtfull, and all children crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. For the ſecond reaſon, which touched out deceaſed Mother, ſhe hath left us at thoſe yeares, that we cannot as yet bemoan, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend well our miſeries. Since we have out-liv'd our childhood, we were never deſirous to prie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your cabinet counſells, to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine your juſtice: Her falt to doe ill ſhould not have made us the more bold, but the more heedfull, and ſtudious to doe well. We be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed our teares upon her only, not to bewaile her death, but to ſatisfie our ſorrowes, ſeeing that our enimies ceaſed not to diſquiet her urne, whole bloud they ſpilt. Father, if our teares which did iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue forth by the command of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, behold crimes at your barre,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:8052:83"/> where ſhall wee finde any ſafety, but in your juſtice? Never among theſe our complaints did there eſcape a hard, or irreverent ſpeech againſt your ſelfe, but indeed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe, who abuſe your au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to the ruine of yours. We have no reaſon to hate your life, but to loue it; and by ſo much the more, in that you have judged us capable, &amp; worthy to inherit your Crown, before all our brethren. You have given us all the enſignes of ſoveraignty, all the honour we can expect; ſo that to demande more were to beg a Licence to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe our ſelves: Why ſhould wee ſeek a Kingdome by a murther, which is to fall to us with your conſent, and good liking, that ſo Heaven, Earth, and Se as conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with <hi>Caeſar</hi> might bar thoſe gates againſtus, to the which wee
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:8052:83"/> would have made a key tempred in the blood of our Father. Your Majeſtie (it may be) hath begot us more unfortunate, then now it were expedient for your eſtate; but we ſhall never be ſo fooliſhly impious, as to commit a villany that would eternally ruine us without recovery. Moſt honour'd Father, expell that fiend of ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which hath poſſeſt you; or if it pleaſe you to entertain it longer we will both part with our lives, whereof wee are not ſo tenderly enamour'd, that we would retain them, with the diſpleaſure of him that gave them.</p>
            <p>This ſpeech attended with the teares of the young Princes did ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh all the Auditors, and as they ſaw them both with dejected eies, expecting the ſentence of the judge, each man burn'd with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:8052:84"/> to ſtand up in their juſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Caeſar</hi> caſts his eyes on <hi>Herod,</hi> who ſhewed himſelfe to be much moved with pitty, &amp; would have wiſht hee had never thought on ſuch an accuſation; for indeed this accuſation did put him much out oſ conceit, and credit with the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, and made him blame his credulity. <hi>Auguſtus</hi> not willing to ſhame him, pronounced that (in truth) the children were much to blame, that they had any way mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſted him; but as for the crime in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, hee ought to raze it out of his Regiſter.</p>
            <p>The young Princes were well bred, and brought up hitherto; it remained that they ſhould live henceforward in good correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and renew the ſacred bond of nature, which could not bee broken by ſo good a father, nor
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:8052:84"/> by the children, who did promiſe ſo much &amp; ſo faire for the future. This being ſpoken, <hi>Herod</hi> embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces his Sonnes one after another with weeping eyes, which drew teares even from thoſe that were no way intereſſed in it.</p>
            <p>After many Leuvoyes, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements, behold them now on their return, together with their father, and brother <hi>Antipater,</hi> who did act (though behinde the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain) all this faire Tragoedy; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe he did captivate them with his curteſies, rejoycing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulating their good ſucceſſe, as if his heart had blaz'd in joyfull fires. So works the tyrannie of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation in Courts untill that God one day take off the maske! Being return'd to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> a yeare did ſcarce run about, before that malice lay'd new giones, to
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:8052:85"/> the innocence of theſe poore Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. <hi>Pheroras</hi> thought within him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to poſſeſſe <hi>Alexanders</hi> head with jealouſie, telling him with much ſecrecy, that his father <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod</hi> did wantonly ſport and dally with <hi>Glaphyra,</hi> his wife, (daughter of King <hi>Archelaus</hi>) judging that this would be a powerfull way to make him revolt, and ſet him all in a rage againſt his father, and ſo to precipitate him to his ruine. Theſe words indeed did very ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fibly touch this noble ſoule, that he began thence forvvard to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve vvith a jealous eye, the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Herod,</hi> vvho in truth plai'd the minion all day with the young Princeſſe, vvho vvas endow'd vvith ſurpaſſing feature, but more he could not diſcover at all in his converſation: ſave the blandiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of a father in Law towards
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:8052:85"/> a daughter, vvorthy to be cheriſht for her many good parts. Yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding <hi>Alexander,</hi> after hee had taken in this ſubtile intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of <hi>Pheroras,</hi> turned this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny into poyſon, interpreting all to the worſt, and was ſo tranſported therewith, that (ruſhing one day to his fathers chamber, he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red unto him the jealouſie, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpition that he had conceived, with many ſighes, and teares of anger. <hi>Herod</hi> vvas much troubled vvith this imputation, &amp; deeming it a thing unbefitting his perſon to ſtir in juſtifying himſelfe vvith multitude of vvords, in excuſe of that vvhich vvanted not any, hee ſaith to him only, my good Son, vvho hath put this into thy head? The other repli'd. That he knew it partly, &amp; <hi>Pheroras</hi> did aſſure him of it. <hi>Pheroras</hi> is preſently ſent for
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:8052:86"/> and <hi>Herod,</hi> vvho d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ever u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e him like a ſervant, frown'd upon him, as though hee vvould have lookt him dead. Thou Rake-hell (quoth he) vvhat haſt thou ſpoken to this young man? It vvas not a tale vvhich thou haſt vvhiſper'd him in the eare, but a ſword thou haſt arm'd his hand vvith againſt his father: for he doth juſtly not to brook acompanion of his bed, no more vvould I of my Realme. U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gratefull vvretch ſhould not thou have torne thy heart out of thy breſt, rather then conceiv'd ſuch a thought of thy brother? The houſe was never tainted with ſuch crimes, nor never ſhal, except thou peſter it with thine: Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k, and let me ſee thee no more; I ordaine tortures for other delinquents, but for thee (in that thou art ſo wicked) I leave thee to the rack of
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:8052:86"/> thine own conſcience, not finding a fitter executioner.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pheroras</hi> nothing amated with this noiſe, anſwered, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat he knew nothing, but what <hi>Salome</hi> (who was there preſent) had told him; as indeed it ſprung from her. But the crafty <hi>Megera</hi> incontinently crying out, and tearing her haire, ſaid, it was a lamentable caſe, that ſhe ſhould be perſecuted by all the world, onely for being faithfull to her brother. <hi>Herod</hi> could not chooſe but ſtand amaz'd to ſee theſe ruptures in his houſe; and he ſaw not in the mean while, that his bad example was the ſourſe &amp; originall of all theſe curſes that befell it. He did nothing to <hi>Phero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras,</hi> but diſcard him for a time: for though he was much incenſt, yet he did not ſtorme in earneſt, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe that hee thought to
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:8052:87"/> conſpire againſt his eſtate; and <hi>Pheroras</hi> ſeem'd to bee none of thoſe, for he was a lewd perſon, a libertine that had married his maid for luſt, refuſing a Kings daughter, &amp; all his thoughts were bent only upon pleaſure. It was by others judg'd that this was no ſufficient penance for <hi>Pheroras</hi> in ſuch a fault, and that this might increaſe the defiance between the Father and his Son. Now ſee the reaſon why <hi>Antipater,</hi> who had alwaies maintain'd his credit with <hi>Herod,</hi> taking hold on this occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, begins the battery more furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly then ever, and having obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſome familiarity between <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander,</hi> and the three Eunuchs, that were moſt entruſted with <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rods</hi> chamber, he gave intelligence under hand, that <hi>Alexanders</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie was all finiſht, &amp; that the
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:8052:87"/> chiefeſt Eunuches about <hi>Herods</hi> chamber were his complices here in. They are forthwith attacht, &amp; tortur'd. Their bodies grown ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feminate with eaſe and delicacie, ſeeing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves ſo rudely pincht, ſpake both what they knew, and what they knew not, and after all, they could not ſpeak any thing, but of the bravery and youthfull boaſtings that had ſlipt from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexanders</hi> mouth, as theſe and the like; That theſe Eunuches were but fooles to adhere to an old do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tard, who did colour his haire for to ſeem young, but it was bootles, his houre-glaſſe was run out, his time was paſt, &amp; theirs was come: that the kingdome could not eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape them, having juſtice, ſtrength, and good credit to their ſide, yea and ſo many ſonnes of <hi>Mars,</hi> men of ſteel, and valour, that would
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:8052:88"/> not faile them in time of need. Such ſpeeches they utter'd, but no ſuch as <hi>Antipater</hi> pretended, and they ſpake too much for a ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous head. It was a miſery to ſee this miſerable Court ſo much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, here was nothing to be heard or ſeen, but accuſations, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiances, diſtruſts and tortures. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man lookt one upon the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and thought he had no other way of ſecurity, but to prevent his companion. They depoſe each day many ridiculous and impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable things that took no effect. There were not found but one or two, that being preſt with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of pain, and to rid them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out, ſaid that <hi>Alexander</hi> had given out in <hi>Rome,</hi> that his father was more inclin'd to the <hi>Parthians</hi> then to the <hi>Romans,</hi> and as they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubled their torments in the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:8052:88"/> of <hi>Antipater,</hi> they did even ſpeak what ever they would have them; as that <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtobulus</hi> had conſpired to make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way their father by poyſon, and then to goe to <hi>Rome</hi> to demand the Crown, which had no ſhew of probability; and as they were askt where was this poyſon? They ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that it was in the Caſtle of <hi>Aſcalon.</hi> And diligent ſearch being made, there was no ſuch matter found: Nevertheleſſe <hi>Alexander</hi> is areſted; hee being of a generous temper, and much moved to ſee executioners ſo buſily imployed, ſpake with a lowd voice to <hi>Herod,</hi> by way of Irony, What needs all theſe butcheries? Since that you will needs be deceived, why I have conſpired againſt your life: And if you deſire to know with whom, it was with <hi>Pheroras,</hi> your
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:8052:89"/> brother and ſiſter <hi>Salome,</hi> with <hi>Ptolomie, Lapritius,</hi> and others of your Conncellers. Kill all the world and you may reigne alone in ſafety. Hee ſpoke too mueh to be believed, and ſpoke it with an accent, that ſpoke nothing leſſe. He is hereupon ſhut up in priſon for ſome daies, untill that <hi>Archelaus</hi> (King of <hi>Capadocia</hi>) his father in law, being advertis'd of this diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, arrives at <hi>Herods</hi> Court. Hee makes with <hi>Herod</hi> no raſh encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, charging him with too much credulity, and the like with a mild temper. This was not the courſe to deale with a man that deſir'd altogether to juſtifie his actions. The <hi>Capadocian</hi> with a mild tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſtrikes ſayle, makes a ſhew of great pitty to ſee him in theſe troubles; ſaying, that his ſons did him great wrong to moleſt him in
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:8052:89"/> this wiſe, that he came thither not to excuſe his own ſon in law, but to puniſh his own daughter, if ſhe were faulty. <hi>Herod</hi> took ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to heare him ſpeak in that manner, that the teares trill'd down his cheeks: And <hi>Archelaus</hi> ſeeing that hee found it fit ſeaſon for perſwaſion, begins by degrees to tell him, that intruth the young Princes ſhew'd ſomewhat too much ſtubbornneſſe, but their youth and gentleneſſe were abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and it were well if this were lookt to. He acted his part ſo well that he at laſt diſpell'd the miſt of calumnie. And <hi>Glaphira</hi> ſeeing her ſelfe now upon the ſtage, did with good language, &amp; her teares carry all ſhee would for her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, ſo that the poore priſoner was forthwith releaſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> began now to live like a
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:8052:90"/> Cyclops in his Cave, walking ſtill in the miſts, and darkneſſe of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſtfull feares, and each moment upon the point to perpetrate freſh cruelties. And when they ſaw him to bee ſo much frighted with ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, <hi>Antipater</hi> did not faile to ſupply him with ſtuffe, and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to feed his ſuſpitions, thereby to advance his own tortunes. There arrives an impoſtor, a <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian</hi> to the Court of <hi>Iudea,</hi> nam'd <hi>Euricles,</hi> in the ſtate, and equipage of a Prince, and beſtowed many preſents on <hi>Herod,</hi> for to inſinuate to his favours. The unhappy King likes well of the man, and places him in the liſt, and number of his moſt intimate friends. Hee did Iodge with <hi>Antipater,</hi> and (ſeeing him predominant in Court) in all his actions hee ſtudied to win his favour, and liking aboue all, which
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:8052:90"/> he did abtain by converſing fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, and familiarly with <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> and fetching the ſecrets of his heart, which hee would after report (true, or falſe) to the eares of <hi>Herod,</hi> who did give him much credit.</p>
            <p>Three yeares being ſcarce paſt over, behold calumnie diſgorgeth the reſt of its venome: Two ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers of <hi>Herods</hi> guard being ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheer'd for ſome light offence, were afterwards imprudently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into <hi>Alexanders</hi> houſe, who did favour them ſeeing they were men of goodly perſonages, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of good ſervice. Theſe are accus'd to have partakt in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy, they are immediatly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended and put upon the rack; the violence of the to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ments forc't them to ſay that by the ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitation of <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulus</hi>
               <pb n="172" facs="tcp:8052:91"/> they had a deſigne upon the perſon of <hi>Herod</hi> for to kill him in hunting. At that very time the Governour of the <hi>Alexandrine</hi> Citadell (which was one of the ſtrongeſt piec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of the Realme) is charged to have promiſed to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray it into the power of theſe young Princes which he did ſtifly renege.</p>
            <p>But his ſon who had ſuffered ſome diſgrace by his father, ſteps out and ſaith the depoſition was true: then hee produc'd letters as from <hi>Alexander,</hi> which confirm'd it, which were thought notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to have come from Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary <hi>Diophantes,</hi> who made a trade of ſuch forgeries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> required no farther proofes, he makes his two ſons to be laid hold on, and reſolves to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them. And indeed every man
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:8052:91"/> from that time forward held them but loſt men. While theſe things were in motion, <hi>Melas</hi> one of the Councellours of the King of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padocia</hi> comes to <hi>Iudea</hi> to knowe where lay the knot and difficulty of the buſineſſe; hee findes the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord very much rankled &amp; feſtred beyond his art and remedies. The wicked father convents his ſonne (calling him from priſon) before <hi>Melas,</hi> there to examine him, and to charge him with ſuch crimes as were depos'd againſt him. <hi>Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> asks where the depone<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts were? It was anſwer'd they were now dead. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e repli'd that this was wrong dealing to put them to death with a lye in their mouthes, which was extorted from them by force of torments, and to ſeale the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> up for ever that they might not deliver the truth. As for him and
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:8052:92"/> his brother <hi>Aristobulus</hi> they had no other intention then to fly to <hi>Capadocia</hi> and thence to <hi>Rome</hi> for to deliver themſelves from the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent hands of their father. When <hi>Herod</hi> heard him ſpeak of the voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age to <hi>Capadocia,</hi> he deſires <hi>Melas</hi> to enquire particularly of <hi>Glaphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra,</hi> if ſhe did not reveal more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence touching this deſigne; who when ſhe law at firſt entry her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band in bolts, it was a pittious thing to ſee how it afflicted her. O my deare husband, ſaith ſhe, are theſe the favours your father be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowes on you! Is this the Diadem that he hath promiſed you? Grief that clogg'd her heart ſmothered the reſt. A ſpring of teares flowed from <hi>Alexanders</hi> eyes, who lov'd her moſt dearely, and all the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany was ſo moved with this pite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſpectacle, that thoſe who ſate
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:8052:92"/> there to examine them, lookt one upon another, and forgot the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality of juſtice. <hi>Herod</hi> demanded of <hi>Alexander</hi> if his wife were not, privy to all his ſecrets, he made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that for her deſerts and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion he, never conceal'd ought from her. The poor Princeſſe was ſomewhat frighted at the ſpeech, yet ſpake very ſimply that ſhe was ignorant of all that was paſt as the child that was yet unborn: how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit ſhe was very ready to tell a ly for to ſave her husband, and ſhee never uſed to diſavow any fault that her husband ſhould tax her with. <hi>Alexander</hi> being toucht to the quick with her pious intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on tells her, <hi>Madam</hi> never won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at it, you know well that I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver had any other drift but to bring you to <hi>Capadocia</hi> to ſee the King your Father; loe that is all
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:8052:93"/> our offence. This did not cure <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod,</hi> but made his ſuſpition yet to extend towards King <hi>Archelaus,</hi> taking it ill that hee would have withdrawn his ſon without his leave, and knowledge: he ſends the priſoners back to their quarter, &amp; in the mean while diſpatcheth new Embaſſadou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to <hi>Rome</hi> for to ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie himſelfe of ſome falſe aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions caſt upon him, &amp; to obtain fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Caeſar</hi> the liberty to diſpoſe of his Children according as juſtice would require, which was gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him. The young Princes were ſo exclaim'd upon &amp; belied with ſuch ſtrange reports at <hi>Rome,</hi> that there was no man would adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to undertake their defence. He being very glad of ſuch ſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſucceſſefull audience (as he was a man ful of formalities, who did alwaies give his paſſions the
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:8052:93"/> gloſſe and tincture of juſtice. He calls a Councel for the arraigning of his ſonnes, admitting all thoſe that he ſaw, and knew to be ill in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, for to favour his intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp; omitting others that might any way divert or hinder them; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong others <hi>Archelaus,</hi> who was expreſſely named by <hi>Caeſar</hi> for to examine the cauſe. Morcover, which was horrible injuſtice, he would not have his ſonnes to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before the Iudges to heare what they could ſpeake in their owne defence, but he enters to the Court full gorg'd with gall and venome; he was never ſeene to change the Copy of his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance ſo much as that time; his paſſions had all tranſſigur'd him in ſuch ſort, that hee ſpake ſuch words, and did ſuch actions as litle beſeem his gravity: his friends
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:8052:94"/> were miſtaken in him, and he ſeem'd to them to be a ſavage ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then a King: ſometimes hee did complaine and lament, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſtood mute and ſtampt for anger; he produced ſome Letters of his ſonnes that carried nothing of weight but only their journey to <hi>Capadocia,</hi> and yet notwitſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, as if he gain'd ſome greatvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, he cryes out, my Maſters, what ſay you to this? See you not this ungracious dealing! O that I had dyed before I had know and ſeen ſuch treachery! Then he ſaith he would referre all to the courſe of juſtice, that he would doe nothing through paſſion, and anon he proclaimes, that he had not called the Aſſembly for to paſſe a Iudgment, but to follow and ſubſcribe to his ſentence, that poſterity might with the more
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:8052:94"/> horror ſpeake of ſuch Parracides, then playing the Scribe or Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loger, he quotes <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> where it is permitted to Fathers to ſtone their rebellious chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to death, then he ſhewes <hi>Caeſars</hi> Letters, which with them carried more ſtrength then his <hi>Deuteronomy,</hi> and inſiſted ſo much upon them, as if the Delinquents had been formerly condemned by the ſentence of <hi>Auguſtus Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar.</hi> When they came to reckon the voices, <hi>Saturnine</hi> a Roman, one of Conſular dignity and great authority, diſwaded plainly this cruelty, telling him that hee was himſelfe a Father, and hee knew what it was to be ſuch a one, and that <hi>Herod</hi> would repent of his raſhneſſe: this good man had three of his ſonnes with him at that time, all gallant men and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:8052:95"/> in places of dignity and truſt, who did plead in favour of the young Princes, but all to no effect. After them ſtarts up one <hi>Volumnius</hi> a rude fellow, who was a prime man, and a leader of the factious file, which was impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell'd to ſerve <hi>Herod's</hi> purpoſes; theſe all with one accord paſt a ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of death moſt unjuſtly: when this arreſt was divulg'd abroad, an old ſouldier of <hi>Herods</hi> guard named <hi>Tero,</hi> much moved with the newes, ſtreight goes to the pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, and deſires to ſpeake with the King in private, which was permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him: This good man taking him aſide uttered his tale ſo ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and withall ſo boldly, that he ſtuck not to ſay that he had loſt his wits, when hee would put to death the true heires for to ſet up a Viper, who in fine would gnaw
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:8052:95"/> his bowels when he thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſafeſt. <hi>Herod</hi> at firſt liſtned to him patiently; but when hee ran on to much on that ſtrain, he askt him who were thoſe that found fault with his proceedings? why that is I (ſaid the old man) &amp; theſe and theſe perſons of quality, which he reckoned unto him. <hi>Herod</hi> ſends him to ſafe cuſtody, while he makes ſure of the reſt, whom he dooms all to die. Then cauſing his ſonnes to be brought all to the City of <hi>Sebaſt,</hi> hee diſpatcheth two of the moſt cruell Lictors that he had in his ſervice, for to ſtrangle them in priſon. The poor Princes, who expected nothing leſſe then ſuch a ſentence, ſeeing the dreadfull viſages of theſe hel-hounds, and the horrid ſhape of death before their eyes, grew pale and bloodleſſe with feare,
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:8052:96"/> and askt them what newes they brought? but they taking them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part like ſheepe aocounted for the ſlaughter, and ſhewing them the inſtrument of death, they plainly diſcover'd the reaſon of their comming; for without any more adoe they tooke them by the throats, &amp; putting the fatall cords about, ſtrangled them by maine force without any mercy. Poore <hi>Glaphira,</hi> who did yet cheriſh a good hope of her husband's deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, when ſhe was a preparing of new batteries to move her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in law to mercy, ſhe heares at once the ſad ſtory of <hi>Alexander's</hi> death, and her owne widdow. hood: ſhe was for a good while in a ſwoune, and after recovery ſtood as mute as a ſtatue, then recolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting her ſpirits, and fetching a deepe and hearty ſigh, Alas quoth
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:8052:96"/> ſhe I never thought that <hi>Herod</hi> would proceed to this! Tell him his ſacrifice of cruelty is not yet compleat: Loe here one moyty of it yet ſurvives. <hi>Alexander,</hi> my deare <hi>Alexander,</hi> that liveſt eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in my heart, muſt thou have ended thy candid innocent daies by ſuch an infamous executioner? Muſt thou have for thy hang-man one whom nature had given for thy Father? Thou ſhouldſt at leaſt have call'd for mee to receive the laſt breathing of thy departing ſoule, to receive thy laſt ſpeeches, &amp; to lay them up in the Cabinet of my heart. Then turning to her two children that were by her ſide: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las poor Orphans, your Father wil no more dandle you, and you muſt now begin your apprentiſhip of miſery in this tender age. The poore Lady did afflict her ſelfe
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:8052:97"/> extremely day and night, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not able to live any longer in the Court of <hi>Iudea,</hi> no more then in a Lion's denne, ſhee was ſent back to <hi>Capadocia</hi> to the King her Father. <hi>Herod</hi> retained her two ſonnes under colour of bringing them up; but indeed for his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſafety, for feare that their name might ſerve for a pretence to ſome revolt.</p>
            <p>O the providenceof the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty! Thou ſeemeſt too tardy in powring vengeance upon the heads of malefactors. Theſe young Princes the children of ſo vertuous a Mother, ſo well edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, &amp; ſo compleat for all good parts, being declar'd heires appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to the Crowne: Theſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, who were ſeene (but five years before) to returne in triumph from <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> like the
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:8052:97"/> two twin-ſtarres that gilded all Paleſtine with their reſplendent beames: Theſe Princes who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd ſo many Trophies, and ſo many wonders, behold them now in their verdant yeares, in the flowre of their hopes, at the gate of the Temple of honour, for a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle freeneſſe in language unmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully maſſacred, and inſteed of a crowne upon their head, die with cords about their necks, ſtrangled by the hands of two of <hi>Herod's</hi> guard! Loe the goodly apprenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and eſſayes that <hi>Herod</hi> made three yeares before the birth of our Saviour for to prepare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for actions, yet more horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and tragicall! It is ſaid of <hi>Sylla</hi> that if mercy her ſelfe were in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane fleſh upon the earth, hee would have ſlaine her; but <hi>Herod</hi> did what was worſe, after ſo many
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:8052:98"/> butcheries his thirſt of blood could not yet be ſatisfied, but im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brues his hands in the blood of 14000 Innocents, and ſeeks to deſtroy the Saviour of mankind, the Son of God himſelfe, as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man knows the ſtory out of holy Writ.</p>
            <p>'Tis now time to ſee the guer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of theſe diſtorted degenerous ſoules, that wee may obſerve the line or courſe of divine provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which doth uſe to inflict ſome exemplary puniſhments here on earth on the wicked, and to give them a reliſh of thoſe eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall paines they ſhall endure in hell.</p>
            <p>Deteſtable <hi>Antipater,</hi> who had contriv'd theſe miſchiefes, ſeeing the two heires of the Kingdome made away by his undermining wit, thought hee had already
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:8052:98"/> mounted halfe the degrees to the Throne: Hee continued in his quaint rogueries, and malicious pranks, ſtill lurking under the maske of piety, as one that had ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme care of the life and ſtate of his Father, ayming in the meane while at no other but then to make himſelfe ſhortly abſolute Lord: And fearing that <hi>Herod's</hi> affection toward him (which was ever wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering and changeable,) ſhould coole, he goes about every day to practiſe great intelligences to make his cards, and winne bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence; but hee was hated of the people as a Tigre, and the ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers that knew him guilty of his brethrens blood (who were ſo wel belov'd of the nobles) could never affect him.</p>
            <p>The Commonalty above all were extremely touch't with com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion,
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:8052:99"/> paſſion, when ever the children of <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Ariſtobulus</hi> (who were brought up in <hi>Herod's</hi> court) were led in the ſtreets. All the world beheld the poore Orphans with weeping eies, and with much anguiſh of ſoule call'd to mind the diſaſters of their Fathers. <hi>Antipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> ſaw well that it was exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dient for him to abſent himſelfe from the Court, both to extinguiſh en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, and that hee might not ſindge his wings by flickering too long about the candle, fearing that in time his Father (who was but too cunning in ſuch matters) would ſent him out and his projects. Yet not withſtanding hee was ſo cloſe, that hee would not openly begge leave of <hi>Herod</hi> for abſence, for feare hee ſhould engender ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but he got his friend at <hi>Rome</hi> (with whom hee dealt under
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:8052:99"/> hand) to write letters to his father in his behalfe, which effected all that he deſired, namely; that it was expedient for him to ſend him to <hi>Rome,</hi> for to breake and divert ſome enterpriſes of the <hi>Arabians</hi> on the Kingdome of <hi>Iudea. Herod</hi> having received theſe Letters, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatcheth him preſently, with a very goodly equipage; with great Preſents, and the Teſtament with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, whereby he was declared King after his fathers deceaſe. Loe for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune hath fill'd the ſayles of his deſires! But as the eye of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty never ſleepes, and takes the crafty in their own imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, it hapned that <hi>Pheroras,</hi> who as we have related, acted his part in this bloody tragoedy, departed this world by a ſuddain death, and poyſon'd as it was thought by the maid which he had married.</p>
            <pb n="190" facs="tcp:8052:100"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> being intreated to goe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to his brothers houſe to make inquiſition of the fact, findes by good warrant and far beſides his thoughts, how that <hi>Antipater</hi> his ſon had ſent <hi>Pheroras</hi> (when he was in diſgrace and out of favour at Court) ſome poyſon for to make away his father then while he was at <hi>Rome,</hi> that ſo he might returne immediatly to <hi>Paleſtine</hi> with his temples girt with a Diadem. This was depos'd by a ſon of <hi>Antipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> farmer, whom hee had made overſeer of his eſtate during his abſence; which was ſeconded with ſuch pregnant &amp; ſtrong preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and evident circumſtances, that there was now nothing left to ſuſpend his beliefe. <hi>Herod</hi> asks where was this poyſon? The young man replied, it was with the window of his brother <hi>Phero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras</hi>
               <pb n="191" facs="tcp:8052:100"/> ſhe being queſtioned concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it got up to an upper roome, pretending to goe and fetch it, but being got up to the top of the houſe, in a deſperate manner ſhee caſts her ſelfe down headlong; but it pleaſed God that this fall proved not mortall according to her deſire. They did incourage her and made all promiſes of impuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, if ſhe would but freely confeſſe the truth: She confeſſeth that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed her husband had a poyſon ſent from <hi>Antipater,</hi> and that hee was once minded for to doe the deed, but it repented him a litle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his death, &amp; he deteſted ſuch wickedneſſe: &amp; upon theſe words ſhee takes out the poyſon which they ſound to be moſt deadly, by making experiment upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd perſons. At that very time <hi>Eathillus</hi> a freeman of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paters</hi>
               <pb n="192" facs="tcp:8052:101"/> was ſurpriſed, comming from <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Iudea,</hi> to adviſe <hi>Phe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roras</hi> to haſten his deſigne, &amp; brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging another poyſon, in caſe the former did not prove effectuall. In the mean time <hi>Antipater</hi> writes to his Father, that hee labour'd dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently at <hi>Rome</hi> to diſpell ſome cloudes of ſlander and to cleare his affaires, which hee hoped to bring about, and to return very ſhortly for <hi>Iudea. Herod</hi> who would have long ſince caught him in his clawes, ſends to him theſe lines;</p>
            <p>Sonne, my declining age &amp; the crazineſſe of my body doe every day inſtruct me that I am mortall, one thing comforts me that I have made choice of your perſon to ſucceed me in my Throne: I ſhall ſee my old age ſpring againe &amp; flouriſh in your and my
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:8052:101"/> death to be ſmother'd (as it were) in your life, ſeeing that I ſhall liue in my other halfe, which is your deare ſelfe. I would you had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſtill neere my perſon, not only for the aſſiſtance your piety ſtill afforded me, but for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice that might acrew to your fortune by your abſence: Faile not therefore with the good leave of <hi>Caeſar</hi> to render your ſelf here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with the beſt ſpeed you can; delay will not any way favour your affaires here. This bayt had charm enough to allure, and art enough to conceale the hook. Vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe news, hee was ready to ride upon the wings of the winde to preſent himſelfe in <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> He diſpatcheth his buſineſſe, takes leave of <hi>Augnſtus,</hi> &amp; makes all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition poſſible to ſhew the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heſts of his father. It was very
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:8052:102"/> ſtrange, that hee could never have any advertiſements by the way of what had paſſed, ſo odious was he to God and man! But being at <hi>Cilicia</hi> hee learnt that his mother was diſcarded and expell'd the Court, which did much affright him, and hee thought to beat his way back againe: But one of his Councell (perchance ſuborn'd by <hi>Herod</hi>) begins to tell him, that if there were nothing intended a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him he needed not to feare, and if any ſlander was broacht of him, hee ought to make the more haſt to quaſh it, other wiſe his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence would but cauſe further ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicion. He ſwallowes the adviſe, and (not withſtanding ſome ſecret reluctancie, &amp; remorſe of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) he followes the road for <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea.</hi> when hee was arrived at the haven of <hi>Sebaſte</hi> he began to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="193" facs="tcp:8052:102"/> into deeper apprehenſions of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then ever; for having ſeen at this very Port not long before at his departure ſuch a throng of people tearing the ayre with their acclamatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, not for any love they owed to him, but to ſhew their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beiſance to <hi>Herod,</hi> who would have it ſo; but he now perceived that fortune had turn'd tail, he was receiv'd with a lowring counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, &amp; ſome did look upon him askue with a quarter face, &amp; mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur'd between their teeth, as cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him for that hee had ſpilt his brethrens bloud. He was engag'd too far on to make retrair, &amp; Gods vengeance had already markt out his lodgings. He goes on from <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baste</hi> ſtrait for <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to the Pallace, ſumptuouſly apparelled, and with a numerous traine: the Gard made way for him
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:8052:103"/> to enter, but were commanded by the King to keep back all thoſe that attended him; hee was quite aſtoniſht to ſee himſelfe caught ſo like a bird in a net, nevertheleſſe he goes on his vvay, enters the hall vvhere his father ſtaid, expecting his approach, accompanied with <hi>Quintilius Varus</hi> lately ſent from <hi>Rome</hi> to bee Governour of <hi>Syria.</hi> When hee had made a moſt reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend ſubmiſſive congy, he drawes neere to kiſſe his father according to the manner of the Countrey, but he ſtraightvvaies heares the roaring of a Lion, for <hi>Herod</hi> dravving a ſtep backe cryes out, Stand aloofe Murtherer, it is not for you any more or any ſuch to receive the welcome kiſſes of a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Behold there Q. <hi>Varus</hi> your Iudge, bethink your ſelfe by to morrow how to anſwer to ſuch
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:8052:103"/> crimes as you are charged with. He was thunderſtrooke with this ſpeech and withdrew himſelf out of the roome with paleneſſe in his face, and the horrour of his crime in his conſcience. In the next chamber he findes his mother and his wife all drencht in teares, who with lamenting eyes had already ſolemniz'd his funerall: ſuch an aſtoniſhment ſeiz'd upon him that hee had neither a tongue to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort them, nor ſo much as teares to bewaile his own misfortunes. He paſt over all the night with much diſquiet of minde, finding now by experiment that it was ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier for to commit a crime then excuſe it. The morrow being come, hee was call'd before the judgement ſeat, where hee found his father with Q. <hi>Varus</hi> &amp; a good number of the Counſellers of
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:8052:104"/> ſtate. Vpon the very point, newes was brought of ſome letters of his mother that were intercepted, which did give him notice that all was diſcover'd, and that he ſhould beware to return and put himſelfe into the hands of his father, if hee would not fall into the jaws of a Lion. This was ſhewed him at his entrie into the Councell<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, hee expected but the houre when he ſhould be ſtrangled, hee was already under the Strapadoes of his conſcience; therefore caſting himſelfe down on his knees, hee begs of his father that hee might not be condemn'd before he vvere heard: <hi>Herod</hi> replies, Varlet what haſt thou to ſay? Hath God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved thee to be the laſt ſcourge of my old age? Thou knoweſt I have taken thee from the bottome and lees of fortune for to place
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:8052:104"/> thee aboue thy brethren, both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond and againſt all hopes. I have put all my treaſures, my revenues, my authority, my affection, my ſecrets, my heart, and my Crowne into thy hands by a teſtament ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with mine own hand, and couldſt not thou expect till thy Fathers eyes were cloſed up by a naturall death, that thou mighteſt freely enjoy them? This was it that thy deſignes did then ayme <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> when thou didſt ſo hotly purſue the death of thy brethren. I have done nothing in their araignment, but by thy denunciation, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. Accurſt wretch, I am afraid that thou haſt ſtain'd mee with their blood; thy crimes doth now giue light to their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> At theſe words hee wept bitterly, recalling to minde his <hi>Mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and unhappy children, hee fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="198" facs="tcp:8052:105"/> his heart ſo oppreſt with ſorrow, that he was faine to entreat his Chancellour <hi>Nicholas Damaſcene</hi> to proceed. <hi>Antipater</hi> prevented him and ſpake in his own defence, That they did him great wrong to believe ſlaves, and women to his prejudice, that he had <hi>Caſars</hi> let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters (whom he could no more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive then God himſelfe) which gave ample teſtimony of his good abeare, and what content he gaue to all at <hi>Rome;</hi> that he was never wanting in his piety towards his Father; and it were a peece of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme folly to thruſt himſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to uncertain dangers for a Crowne that he was certain of, and had in his own hands. Briefly, not to make a longer diſcourſe, that hee offered himſelfe to be uſed like a ſlave, and to bee ſet upon the rack to prove his innocence. And ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:8052:105"/> this he did rave, and ſtamp in a fearefull manner, inſomuch that he began to move all the bench to pitty and wonder. <hi>Nicholas Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcene</hi> being a ſtern and rough Iudge, takes him in hand, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts him with witneſſes, canvaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him, preſſeth, puzles, &amp; quite confounds him, then diſchargeth a invective againſt him, exaggerating (like an Orator) all the circumſtances of his crime. Is it not (ſaith he) a brutiſh ſtupidity to conſpire againſt your Father, the bloud of your brethren being as yet before your eyes, and all the aſſurances of a Scepter in your hands. muſt a man needs be a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricide for to bee poſſeſſour of a Crown which was bequeathed you by Teſtament ſo ſolemne and authentick? Did you expect any more then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat your Fathers
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:8052:106"/> blood ſhould be the ſeal? and ſuch a father whoſe life is precious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all good men, and whoſe nature is ſo indulgent in favour of his children, deſerve they never ſo litle. An ingratitude able to make heaven to bluſh, and the earth to tremble under our feet, yea and worthy that all the elements ſhould conſpire to chaſtiſe it. The man ran on thus in fire and fury; powring out a torrent of words, while the wreteh <hi>Antipater</hi> with a dejected countenance pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'d God to work ſome miracle in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half for to manifeſt his innocence, ſeeing that he was mercileſly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt by the malice of his adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. It is ſtrange that a man who had no god in his life time, would now ſeek one at his death. This ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lived as though there were neither heaven nor Hell, and ſeeing him
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:8052:106"/> ſo neere the brink of death, he beſough a Daity to patronize his offence. <hi>Varus</hi> ſpeaks to him, my friend, expect not any extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſignes from heaven on your behalfe, but if you haue any ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous reaſon or Apologie produce it into evidence, the King your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſires nothing more then that you might quit your ſelfe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. Vpon this hee was confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as a loſt man. <hi>Varus</hi> taking the poyſon which was brought to the judgement ſeat caus'd it to be giuen to a Malefactour that was ſentenced to death, who died im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly in the place; whereupon all the aſſembly aroſe forth with, thereby giving manifeſt token of <hi>Antipater's</hi> condemnation. His Father now holding him for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vict, demands of him who were his complices, he nam'd but <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="202" facs="tcp:8052:107"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Philus</hi> only who had brought the poiſon, and ſaid that that Varlet had been the cauſe of his undoing. It wanted but litle, that <hi>Herod</hi> did not then preſently execute the ſentence of death; but according to his ordinary proceedings he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to acquaint <hi>Caeſar</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with firſt, and to ſend him the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe with full inſtructions of the examination, that ſo he might doe according to his good pleaſure. In the mean while <hi>Antipater</hi> is ſhut up in cloſe priſon, expecting each day (like a piacular victime) the fatall ſtroak.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Herod</hi> moreover had now about threeſcore and ten yeares upon his back, and by the feebleneſſe of his age perceived the ſignalls of deaths approch: This was a bit very tough to digeſt, never did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man love this life ſo well; hee
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:8052:107"/> had verily parted with his portion in the other world, that hee might enjoy this forever, for that, indeed he was ſuperlatively wicked. To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his later daies hee grew ſo penſive and thenſo cholerick, and furious, that his domeſtick ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts knew not how to boord him. Hee was in his Court like an old Lion bound in the chaines of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable diſeaſes: Hee perſwaded himſelfe, that hee was hated of all the world, and hee was not decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in his opinion, for hee had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven but too much occaſion.</p>
            <p>The people burſt the yoke of duty and allegiance, and could no longer endure him. As ſoon as the rumour ran of his ſickneſſe, <hi>Iudes</hi> and <hi>Mathias,</hi> two of the moſt famous Doctors of the Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh law, who had all the youth of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> under their charge, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtigated
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:8052:108"/> ſtigated ſome of the boldeſt of their ſect unto a ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>turous attempt, as thus. <hi>Herod</hi> having reëdified &amp; much beautified the Temple of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> (as hee had alwaies ſhewed himſelfe for his own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terreſts an Idolater of <hi>Caeſars</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune,) caus'd on the chiefeſt gate thereof to bee planted the <hi>Roman Eagle</hi> which glittered all in gold: This was a great eye-ſore to the <hi>Iews,</hi> who never could endure any ſhape of man or beaſt within their Temples: ſo much did they abhor theſe monſters which their fathers in <hi>Aegypt</hi> ador'd. Loe this was the reaſon why <hi>Iudas M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>athias,</hi> who were as the principall men (thinking that <hi>Herods</hi> ſickneſſe fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd their purpoſes) began to exhort in good earneſt the moſt valiant of the young men that fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented their houſes, to take in
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:8052:108"/> hand Gods quarrell according to the noble ſpirits of their anceſters and to batter down this abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that was advanc'd upon the Temple: the danger was not now ſo great, <hi>Herod</hi> being cumbred with buſineſſes and diſeaſes, but if it ſhould happen that any ſhould looſe his life, to dye in ſo good &amp; glorious an act was to dye trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant, and Laurells would grow up out of their tombes. They faild not to ſpur up theſe younkers, &amp; to ſet an edge on their courage, with many ſpecious and plauſible arguments. Loe a regiment of the moſt reſolute of them, goes forth at mid-day, arm'd with axes and hatchets, who ſcale the Temple &amp; quaſh in pieces the Eagle in the ſight of all the world; <hi>Judas</hi> and <hi>Matthias</hi> being then preſent, and ſerving as trumpets to the ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:8052:109"/> The noiſe arriv'd preſently at Court, the Captain of the Guard runs thither with a maniple of the hardieſt ſouldiers, hee was afraid of ſome greater matter towards, &amp; that this demolition was but a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litation, or skirmiſh of a greater tumult. But at firſt onſet, when he began to charge, the people did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, which did encourage him to fall on, and to follow cloſer: forty young men that were buſieſt were taken in the place, <hi>Iudas</hi> and <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias</hi> bearing them company, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it a diſhonour to recoile, and that they ought to follow them at leaſt into danger, whom they at firſt had lead into miſchiefes. As they were preſented to <hi>Herod,</hi> and being askt whence proceeded that inſolent preſumption and raſhnes, they frankly anſwered that the buſineſſe had been conſulted of, &amp;
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:8052:109"/> well diſcuſt among them, and if it were yet to be done, they were ready to put into execution: foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as they were more oblig'd to obey <hi>Moſes</hi> then <hi>Herod. Herod</hi> ſome what ſtartled with their reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, and fearing greater com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions, caus'd them ſecretly to be convey'd to <hi>Ierico,</hi> whether himſelf was carried, though weak and ſickly. Then aſſembling the chiefeſt of them, he ſpeaks to them from his couch, making a large narration of the good offices hee had done to that nation, of the Temple which he had built, the ornaments with which he did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich in; adding that in few yeares he had done what their <hi>Haſſamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nean</hi> Kings could not in 120, and in recompence of his piety they went at high-noon to violate with ſtrange inſolence a ſacred dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:8052:110"/> he beſtowed on the Temple, in the which God was more inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſed then himſelfe, and therefore he did ſo much the more require a reaſon of this attempt.</p>
            <p>Theſe men fearing to awake his anger, further did falſifie &amp; clude the blow, and did transfer it all on their companions, abandoning them to the diſcretion of the king. Thereupon the Prieſt hood was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away from <hi>Matthias,</hi> and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other <hi>Matthias,</hi> who was held to be a ring-leader in the ſedition, was burnt alive with his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions that ſame night, at which time was ſeen an ecclipſe of the Moon, which made the ſpectacle yet more terrible. <hi>Herod</hi> ſome few daies after having tried, and ſpent in vain all humane remedies, was brought into a miſerable ſtate of ſickneſſe, which is pertinently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:8052:110"/> by <hi>Ioſephus</hi> and <hi>Enſebius.</hi> It was Gods pleaſure hee ſhould drink often and deep of the cup of his juſtice in this life, waſting his wretched body with tedious paines. therefore hee was ſmote from heaven, and was charged with a fierce ſquadron of incura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſeaſes, he that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his youth up did bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with a furious ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, felt at his death a greedy fire feeding on his entralls: hee that all his lifetime, had an inſatiable thirſt of a maſſing treaſure (inſomuch that he digg'd up the tombes of <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi> for to ranſack the ſpoiles) was tormented with a Dog appetite; a horrible diſeaſe, and which modeſty feares to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeribe, which made him cry out for hunger, eating day and night and could not be ſatisfied, hee that made ſo many voiages and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:8052:111"/> ſo many atchievements to raiſe himſelfe aboue the levell of ordinary fortunes, ſaw then his feet ſwolen with redundant hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours. He that practis'd ſo many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ortures in his life time, was now rackt with the violent and intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable pangs of a Chollick: he that bereav'd ſo many men of their breath, did now draw breath with much difficulty and pain: He that held humane wiſdome and polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie for the nerves and ſtrength of his eſtate, felt now in his body ſuch Cramps and Convulſions of Nerves and Sinewes, that hee was ſorely and pittifully ſhaken: Hee that had ſhed poore <hi>Mariamnes</hi> blood, murther'd her Sonnes for to make the Kids boile in the milk of the Damme, as the Scripture ſpeaks: Hee that had imbrued his hands in the bloud of about</p>
            <pb n="211" facs="tcp:8052:111"/>
            <p>14000 innocents with an intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to involve the Saviour of the world in that generall maſſacre died in his own bloud afflicted with a cruell diſſentry. He that had abuſed his member. with mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous luxurie was over-run and conſum'd with an army of Lice, acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panied with an ignominious ſatiriaſme, a diſeaſe which I ſcarce dare name. And now, ſay the eye of providence is not awakt for the puniſhing of delinquents. This deſperate wretch at his death in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteed of adoring the juſtice of God and kiſſing the rod that gave him correction, thinks on now ſlaughters. Hee aſſembles by an edict the moſt principall of the lewes out of every Province un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Ierice,</hi> and having pounded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> within the cirque hee calls to him his Siſter <hi>Salome</hi> and her husband</p>
            <pb n="212" facs="tcp:8052:112"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander,</hi> and addreſſeth his ſpeech unto them in this manner.</p>
            <p>It grieves mee not at all to dye and to render that tribute to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which ſo many Kings before me have paid. But it troubles mee that my death wil not be ſo much bemoaned as I could wiſh, if you doe refrain your hands. Know then that for this purpoſe I have ſent for theſe Nobles of <hi>Irdea;</hi> As ſoone as ever death ſhall draw theſe Curtaines over mine eyes, let them all fall by the edge of the ſword, and let not my death be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulg'd before that the newes of theſe mens death arrive at each ones Country and kindred. By this meanes I hope to fill all <hi>Iudea</hi> with lamentation and woe, which will be muſick to my ſoule as her laſt departure. This pernicious fiendin thus ſpealing, be fought</p>
            <pb n="213" facs="tcp:8052:112"/>
            <p>Siſter with hot teares, by all that ſhe eſteemed in the world moſt precious &amp; ſacred, &amp; as ſhe hoped for Paradiſe, to perform his wil, and to give him content: ſhe muſt promiſe it with an oath at that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry inſtant, though afterwards it was not at all put in execution.</p>
            <p>In this ſole act hee ſhewed that he was not inform'd with a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſoule, he was but a wolfe in mans skin and ſhape, and that the thirſt of humane bloud was now chang'd into his nature. As hee was making this goodly Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Letters were brought him from <hi>Caeſar</hi> which did acquaint him that one <hi>Acme</hi> a lewiſh Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, who was of the train of <hi>Livia</hi> the wife of <hi>Augustus,</hi> had beene convicted of bad intelligence with <hi>Antipater,</hi> and was therefore pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht with death, as for his ſonnes
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:8052:113"/> hee referr'd them wholly to his own diſpoſall. This man at the point of death ſuckt revenge yet with wonderfull pleaſure. This newes was balme to his tortur'd carcaſe, he calls for an apple and a knife, thinking to pare it himſelfe, but thereupon his paines (that had given him but ſhort truce) aſſaild him with double force, ſo that he was quite weary of his life which he had ſo dearely lov'd. One of his grand children nam'd <hi>Achia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> who at that time ſtood neere the bed, perceived that hee rolled his eyes furiouſly, and lookt as though he would have rid himſelf of his torments with the knife hee had in his hand, which did much affright the young Prince, who holding his arme as gently as hee could, hee beganne to cry out, as though his good father had yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:8052:113"/> up the Ghoſt, wherewith the whole Court was muſtered up. <hi>Antipater</hi> out of his priſon over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard the tumult, and ſuſpected that <hi>Herod</hi> was a dying, he did not yet deſpaire of the Crown, offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring mountaines (as wee ſay) of gold to his Warder to let him eſcape.</p>
            <p>But behold the judgement of God! the keeper of the priſon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteed of all the ample rewards that were promiſed him, and which he might have enjoyed, he goes ſtrain way to the Father and relates to him how that. <hi>Antipater</hi> had urg'd him withall ſupplications &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes to let him looſe out of the priſon, that he might take poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the kingdome. <hi>Herod</hi> ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing and beating his head, cries out. what will the villain murther mee in my bed, I have yet life enough
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:8052:114"/> to take away his, then raiſing him ſelfe a litle upon the boulſter, and leaning upon his elbow, he cals to one of the Guard, goe you (quoth he) hence to the priſon &amp; kill that parrici<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e there, and let him be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terred in the Caſtle of <hi>Hyrcanus</hi> with out any Rites, or ſolemnities of a funerall. This was inſtanrly executed, and ſuch was the end of this unhappy thing, who mov'd Earth and Hell for to mount his fathers throne, according as ſome Matherfaticians had foretold.</p>
            <p>Five daies being exphed from the death of <hi>Antipater, Herod</hi> after he had declared <hi>Arche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aus</hi> for his Succed out in the Realme, contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> determinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he had deſigned it for <hi>Antipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> after he had aſtorted to his two other Sonnes ſuch portions as hee thought good, and beqdeathed
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:8052:114"/> large Legacies to <hi>Auguſt us Caeſar</hi> he gave up his wretched ſoule in rage, and deſpaire, in the yeare of his life threeſcore and ten, and of his raigne 37. A man (ſaith <hi>loſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi>) whoſe actions alwaies over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rul'd the Lawes, land his paſſions them, who notwithſtanding all his proſperity was eſteem'd the moſt miſerable man in the world. Mark how this Author ſpeaks, who was a wiſe Stateſman to inſtruct hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane pollicy, that there is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wiſdome, nor greatneſſe, nor happineſſe where God is wanting. For to let paſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> eternall tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich this barbaro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nder the hand of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. I am verily perſwad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> there is no Peſant, nor Hin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> (if he be not ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid) would change one day of his life for the thirty ſeven yeares of</p>
            <pb n="218" facs="tcp:8052:115"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Herods</hi> raigne, which hee paſt in continuall jealouſneſſe, trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome affaires, perilous voyages, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter miſtruſts, barbarous cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and remorſe of conſcience, which is the harbenger, &amp; pream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Hell. Leaving more o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver behinde him a nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and unhappy Poſterity.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:8052:115"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
